<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of some assertions relating to coin and trade from the reflections made by the author of the essay on ways and means, in his book, intituled, Discourses on the publick revenues, and on the trade of England,&amp;c. part. II.</title>
            <author>Davenant, Charles, 1656-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 232 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2780A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218299</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829907</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829907</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34354</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55328)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34354)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2012:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of some assertions relating to coin and trade from the reflections made by the author of the essay on ways and means, in his book, intituled, Discourses on the publick revenues, and on the trade of England,&amp;c. part. II.</title>
                  <author>Davenant, Charles, 1656-1714.</author>
                  <author>Pollexfen, John, b. ca. 1638, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 128, 131-180 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Geo. Graston, in the Middle-Temple-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text and register are continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>With an initial index.</note>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to John Pollexfen. However, "Discourses on the publick revenues" is by Charles Davenant. Cf. Wing D306.</note>
                  <note>Copy has attribution to "Dr. Charles D'Avenant" in MS. on A1v.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Coins, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Legal tender --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Commerce --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34354:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF SOME ASSERTIONS Relating to Coin and Trade, FROM THE REFLECTIONS Made by the Author of the Eſſay on <hi>Ways</hi> and <hi>Means,</hi> In his Book, intituled, DISCOURSES ON THE <hi>Publick Revenues, and on the Trade of</hi> ENGLAND, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Part. II.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Geo. Grafton,</hi> in the <hi>Middle-Temple-Lane.</hi> 1699.
<pb facs="tcp:34354:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:34354:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:34354:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34354:3"/>
            <head>INDEX.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE danger of Erroneous poſitions referring to Trade <hi>Page 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Propoſitions offered to be conſider'd <hi>p. 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diſtinctions between the Riches of the individuals and the Riches of the body Politick <hi>p. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That Computations of Riches depend much upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, and that we ought to diſtinguiſh between Riches ariſing from our annual Crops and Labour at home, and Riches gotten by Foreign Traffick <hi>p. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That particular men will have little comfort in their acquiſition of Riches, unleſs the body politick have at the ſame time a ſtock of ſuch Riches, as may be uſeful to preſerve them in a quiet enjoyment <hi>p. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That Gold and Silver is the moſt uſeful Treaſure for that End, when converted into Coin, and that it is the only Treaſure that can be acquired by Foreign Trade, for the general uſe of all <hi>p. 8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How neceſſary it is we ſhould have of it in proportion to our Neighbours <hi>p. 10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If not, how all our enjoyments will be in a precarious condition <hi>p. 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That as it is neceſſary for our defence, ſo alſo for the carrying on of Trade, and for keeping up the value of Lands <hi>p. 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That we ought not to part with it for corruptible Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, becauſe the want of it cannot be ſupplied by any Coin of baſer Metals <hi>p. 13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the want of Coin in the Nation will put an end to the uſe of Paper Credit <hi>p. 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:34354:4"/>Why Gold and Silver Coin may claim a prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Paper Credit <hi>p. 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Examination of the arguments uſually given for the Exportation of Coin, and for ſupplying the want of it, by Paper Credit <hi>p. 18.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How the want of Coin (if care be not taken) will inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly come upon us, and not be perceived till felt <hi>p. 20.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Aſſertions made by the Author of <hi>the Eſſay on Ways and Means, That Money is no more at the bottom then Counters to reckon with, a choak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Commodity,</hi> &amp;c. Examined <hi>p. 24.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Author's opinion for ſetting up a new meaſure of Commerce, Examined <hi>p. 28.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The inconſiſtency of the Author's own opinions, as to the uſe and Value of Coin, and how contrary to <hi>Xenophon</hi>'s <hi>p. 29.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Second propoſition conſider'd <hi>p. 33.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The danger of allowing that all extended Traffick en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riches a Nation <hi>p. 34.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The uſe of enquiries how a Nation may get or loſe, and what advantages we have by Trade <hi>p. 35.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the gaining of conveniences and advantages are the natural conſequences of Trade, but that the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Treaſure is difficult <hi>p. 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the bulk of Trade affords only Conveniencies, not Treaſure <hi>p. 38.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the gaining of Treaſure by Foreign Traffick, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the bringing into the Nation of ſome Species, durable and uſeful for the body Politick, and that the Original of our Riches is from our annual Crops, and what we get out of the bowels of the Earth and Sea, improved by Labour <hi>p. 41.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the we have great conveniencies by our Domeſtick Trades, that yet our Riches can only change hands by them <hi>p. 42.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the advantages ariſing by Trades carried on by the Exportation of our Products, or by Goods procured by them, and the danger that may be feared from Trades carried on by the Exportation of Bullion <hi>p. 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:34354:4"/>No Eſtimates can be made whether a Nation get or loſe by any Trade, unleſs Conſumption be conſider'd as a part of Trade <hi>p. 46.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That we ſhall not get Treaſure by Foreign Trade, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out agreeing upon proper methods <hi>p. 51.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What ſteps our Anceſtors took to increaſe our Trade and Treaſure <hi>p. 52.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How we have deviated from thoſe methods, ſince the year <hi>1666 p. 54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The reaſons why <hi>an. 1666</hi> is fixt for the year of our declenſion <hi>p. 54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Ways and Means to get Treaſure by Foreign Trade <hi>p. 57.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to examine whether we have taken ſuch methods ſince <hi>ann. 1666 p. 58.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the impoſſibilities we have been under to get Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by our Foreign Trade, ſince the year <hi>1666. p. 61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Arguments from the ſtate of our Coin, that we have decreaſed our Treaſure ſince <hi>ann. 1666 p. 64.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That we have not only conſumed much of the old Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Coin we had before <hi>1666,</hi> but alſo all the Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Bullion that was brought in by our good Trades between the year <hi>1666</hi> ond <hi>1688 p. 66.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That Gold money was never ſo uſeful for the ſervice of all, or in caſe of an exigency as Silver Money. <hi>p. 68.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the improvement of Lands, increaſe of quick Stock, Houſes, and Ships, are not to be allowed as an inſtance of Riches gotten by Foreign Traffick <hi>p. 69.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the increaſe of the Cuſtoms is no proof that we have got Riches by Foreign Trade, ſince the year <hi>1666 p. 70.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Nor coſtly Furniture, Apparel, Equipage, or Stock in Iron, Lead, Tin, <hi>&amp;c. p. 71.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That this Nation has ſet out great Fleets, or maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed great Armies, not allowed as a proof, that we had not conſumed much of our Treaſure by Trade before the War <hi>p. 72.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:34354:5"/>A Fundamental poſition laid down as to Trade in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>p. 73.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That a Stock of Silver Coin can only be depended on, for the conſtant uſe of the Government and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, with a Computation of what we may now have <hi>p. 76.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How much of it muſt be allotted for Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, payment of Rents and petty Expences, and circulate for thoſe uſes only <hi>p. 77.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Arguments that we have decreaſed our Coin, from the price of Bullion <hi>p. 78.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Anſwers to the ſeveral Objections and Reflections made by the Author of <hi>the Eſſay on Ways and Means,</hi> intermixt with ſeveral Arguments and Diſcourſes about Trade, and detections of Errors in his Computations from Page <hi>81</hi> to the End.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34354:5"/>
            <head>A VINDICTION OF SOME ASSERTIONS Relating to Coin and Trade, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>ALL endeavours to come to an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement in Notions, that may tend to improve our Trade, and render it more beneficial, ought to be encouraged, leaſt the Treaſure of the Nation be conſumed, whilſt we are diſputing, which is the way to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and increaſe it, erroneous Poſitions and miſtaken Maxims if fundamental and put in practice, will have the ſame effect in the management of Trade, as errors near the Center in erecting of Schemes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:34354:6"/>Tho all men agree, that the end and buſineſs of Foreign Trade is to acquire Riches and obtain a Treaſure, yet there are different Opinions, what Species, Goods, or Commodities deſerve to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed the Treaſure of the Nation, and may be the moſt uſeful and ſerviceable Riches <hi>or Treaſure:</hi> as likewiſe whether we have got or loſt by our Foreign Trade, as it has, of late years been carried on, and how Trade ought to be direced or managed, that we may enrich our ſelves and increaſe our Treaſure by it. As a means to reconcile theſe Opinions, and to vindicate ſome Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions formerly printed upon the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, theſe Propoſitions are offer'd to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> That Gold and Silver deſerve to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed the moſt uſeful Treaſure of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that it is the only Species brought in by foreign Trade, convertible into a National Stock, for both publick and private uſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> That tho moſt Trades afford great conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences and advantages, yet that it is diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to get Treaſure from foreign Nations by Trade, and that we have decreaſed our Treaſure ſince the year <hi>1666</hi> by foreign Trade.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In order to make a judgment upon the firſt Propoſition, it is premiſed, that tho the Riches of the whole Body united under a Government, or Body Politick, in which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34354:6"/>ſence the word <hi>Nation</hi> muſt be underſtood, do moſtly conſiſt of Riches in the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the individuals, and that all ſorts of Goods which any man has in his cuſtody, and may be converted into Money, or made uſefull for him or his Family, may deſerve to be eſteem'd that Man's Riches, tho periſhable, and ſubject to corruption, yet that all ſuch, ought not be eſteemed the Treaſure of the Nation, nor all gain made on foreign Traffick, by particular perſons, an addition to the Wealth and Stock <hi>or Treaſure</hi> of the whole Body Politick.</p>
            <p>When we judge of the Wealth of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Men, thoſe only are eſteemed Rich, that have Lands, Houſes, Jewels, Money, or what elſe may be accounted laſting and valuable, over and above what is neceſſary for their uſe, and ſupport; thoſe which have only Goods, or Conveniencies, for the ſupply of their neceſſities, or ſpend their riches as faſt as they get them, are not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed Rich, the like diſtinction ought to be made in computing the Riches of the Nation, between ſuch Commodities that are only uſeful to ſupply its neceſſity, or elſe conſumed as ſoon as procured, or only valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able among our ſelves, and thoſe Goods and Commodities that are durable, and are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued in moſt parts of the World.</p>
            <p>And as all computations of riches depend
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34354:7"/>much upon compariſon, and a particular Perſon, may be thought rich, becauſe he has more than his Neighbours, ſo when we make an eſtimate of the riches or Treaſure of the Nation, we ought to have reſpect to foreign Nations, and the compariſon muſt be between Nation and Nation, whether we are rich in proportion to them, or have now in the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſuch Species, or Commodities, as may be properly called the Riches of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, compared with our neighbouring Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that may be valuable in all places, and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for making an offenſive or defenſive War.</p>
            <p>If upon inquiry it appear, that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal of our riches is from the labour of our People, by improving what they get out of the bowels of the Earth and Sea, and the annual Crops of our Land, and that tho we uſually by foreign Trade get Commodities that are convenient for us, and ſuch Species as may beſt deſerve to be eſteemed Treaſure, yet that the proportion, which we bring in of Gold or Silver, or any ſort of Goods that may deſerve to be eſteemed the Riches of the Nation, is inconſiderable to what we bring home, in periſhable Commodities, then no credit ſhould be given to Eſtimates of Treaſure gotten from Foreigners and brought into the Nation by foreign Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick, notwithſtanding the great bulk of our Trade, unleſs it be aſcertained in what Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34354:7"/>or Commodities it conſiſts, and ſome demonſtration be given where ſuch Riches may be found; for the conveniencies ariſing from Trade ought not to be taken as an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Wealth, and much of the Wealth, we have; was not procured by foreign Traffick, as people have increaſed with time, ſo manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and improving of Lands, working of Mines, and building of Houſes have increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of courſe, which has occaſioned an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of quick Stock, the manufacturing of goods at home by our own People, for the Furniture of Houſes, for Cloathing, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other uſes, all which ſeveral Species of Riches and many others that might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced, now in our poſſeſſion were never procured by foreign Traffick, but by the advantages, we have, by nature, improved by the labour and induſtry of our People, which ought to be ſeparated and diſtinguiſht from what we have got by foreign Traffick, that we may not be miſlead, to neglect our concerns at home, and run into errors that may occaſion the conſuming of what we have, on a ſuppoſition that it is eaſie to get Riches from Foreigners by Trade, which upon a further enquiry will be found very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult.</p>
            <p>And as theſe things ought to be conſidered in the valuation of our Riches, ſo a difference muſt be made, between the intereſt of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34354:8"/>whole Body united under a Government for common defence, and the particular intereſt of every individual which compoſes that Body for tho each individual depends on the Body Politick for protection in his Liberty and Property, yet in the acquiring Wealth few apply their thoughts to that which may be for the intereſt and advancement of the Wealth of the Nation in general, or extend their endeavours further than how to gain ſuch Species or Commodities by Trade or otherways, as may be uſeful as Riches to them, and their Families: But it is the intereſt of the Government it ſelf, to take care that ſuch Riches may be gotten and retained as may moſt tend to the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the whole Body, and to diſcourage and prevent all methods and practices uſed by particular perſons in procuring of Wealth for themſelves, which may tend to diminiſh and conſume what may moſt properly be called the Treaſure of the Nation.</p>
            <p>The acquiſitions or riches of particular Men, will be of little comfort to them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs gain'd and enjoy'd with a proſpect o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſecurity and quiet poſſeſſion, therefore thoſe Species or Commodities will deſerve to be eſteemed the beſt Wealth or Treaſure of the Nation, (next after, what are neceſſary to ſupply the cravings of Nature) that may be depended on, as a laſting durable Stock,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34354:8"/>capable, to be collected for the Service of the Government, for the compoſing and procuring of Fleets and Armies, the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an offenſive or defenſive War, and for defraying the charges neceſſary for the preſervation of the publick Peace againſt foreign Invaſions, and domeſtick Troubles.</p>
            <p>Tho Lands, Houſes, Jewels, Forts, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Ships and all durable Commodities, whether in poſſeſſion of the Government or particular perſons, may deſerve to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed riches, yet upon an enquiry it will appear, that they cannot be made uſeful for the defence of the Nation, but by the help of Coin.</p>
            <p>Lands and Houſes and all the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Lands encreaſe of Building, may advance the Kings Revenues when a Tax is laid on Land, but unleſs ſuch Taxes do produce Money, the Lands and Houſes will rather be a temptation to an Enemy, than ſerviceable to our defence, or enable us to make oppoſition.</p>
            <p>Jewels; Furniture and ſuch like, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their value aſcertained, nor being cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to be divided into ſmall denominations, and uſually in the hands of ſuch as keep them either for their private Delight, or O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation, cannot be ſo uſeful for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Fleets and Armies, nor for the preſervation of the Kingdom as Coin.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:34354:9"/>Quick Stock on Lands tho of great uſe for the furniſhing of Proviſions and other neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rys for Fleets, and Armies, yet cannot be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly procured or obtained without Coin.</p>
            <p>People, Ships, Braſs, Iron, Lead, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and all other Commodities and Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarys for War, muſt be made ſerviceable for thoſe ends, by the help of Coin: Without it, or an expectation thereof, the People cannot be kept in a Body, nor Ships equipt, nor any of the engines or materials for War made uſefull.</p>
            <p>And as Gold and Silver, after it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into Coin is ſo abſolutely neceſſary for the carrying on of all Affairs, both Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and Private, ſo in its nature being beſt fitted for it, is moſt likely to circulate and to be ſeldom hoarded up, becauſe of the profit which uſually follows the lending or uſing of it, and therefore it may be ſaid to be the <hi>only Treaſure</hi> that can be acquired by foreign Trade, for the general uſe of all the Nation, Jewels and moſt other Species as they are not qualified for circulation, ſo they are uſually but as a dead Stock, not only to the Publick, but to thoſe that have them.</p>
            <p>Common practice and experience have ſufficiently evinced that theſe Aſſertions are in a great meaſure true, and alſo that the generality, or body of the People, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34354:9"/>to the defence of the Nation, by pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or advancing of Coin, if they have plenty of that, it may be drawn from them to pay Taxes, or upon Loans, as the exigencies of the Government may require; But as they would be unwilling to part with their Lands Houſes, Jewels, Furniture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo no way was ever yet invented to make an equal or general collection of them, and if it could be done, ſuch Goods would never prove very uſeful for the defence of the Nation, without Coin.</p>
            <p>All Taxes, Impoſitions, and Dutys charg'd on the people, for the uſe of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are made payable in Coin, as moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, for uniting and cementing, the ſtrength of the Nation, and defraying the Charges of the Government: As ſcarcity uſually makes all valuable things dear, and hard to be procured, ſo a ſcarcity of Coin, will make it hard to be got to pay Taxes, or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Loans raiſe <hi>praemiums,</hi> increaſe the Debts of the Nation, and put the people under greater difficulties, to pay what Taxes may be charged upon them.</p>
            <p>Tallies, Bank-Notes, ſhares in the Bank, and in other Joynt-Stocks, in which a great part of the Eſtates of ſome particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons do conſiſt, and in which the Publick alſo is much concerned, if caſt up would amount to a very great ſum, the Paper or Wood,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34354:10"/>the perſons concerned, have to ſhew for ſuch Debts, Shares, or Stocks, is worth nothing of it ſelf, therefore the repute or eſteem, which ſuch Stocks or Tallys have, muſt ariſe from an expectation of reaching ſomething valuable, and it not being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the Landed Men, will part with their Lands, nor the Ladys with their Jewels, to ſatisfie ſuch expectation; it is preſumed it muſt be Coin that is expected, a want of that, will ſoon depreciate the value put upon ſuch Tallys, Joynt-Stocks, or Notes, and render them to be of little uſe.</p>
            <p>And as Coin doth appear thus to be uſeful, to make our Lands, Houſes, Joynt-Stocks, or what elſe we may eſteem real or artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Treaſure ſerviceable, for the defence of the Nation, or uſeful and valuable for our ſelves, ſo it is abſolutely neceſſary we ſhould have of it in proportion to our Neighbours, for it hath been found by late experience, that the event of Wars, may depend upon the ſtrength of the Purſe, as well as upon the length of the Sword, that Nation which hath ſtore of Coin, may have Auxiliary Troops, and foreign Aſſiſtance, to make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or procure recruits, and recover any loſs, they may ſuſtain; but thoſe that have it not, muſt depend ſolely upon their own ſtrength, and be in no good condition to collect or unite what they may have to make
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34354:10"/>it ſerviceable: And in caſe of Famine thoſe Nations will be under the greateſt difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to get ſupplies, that are not ſtored with Gold and Silver.</p>
            <p>Whether Gold and Silver have ſo great an eſteem, becauſe of its natural qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications to ſerve for many uſes, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of its ſcarcity, and the difficulties and labour that muſt be undergone to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it, or becauſe of its durableneſs (yet malleable) and capable to receive any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and to be divided under ſeveral denominations, or becauſe by the univerſal conſent of Nations, it is become the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of Commerce, and Dealings, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it would decline from the value now put on it, if it ſhould grow plenty; or whether any people make a ſhift to ſupport themſelves without it; or whether Money doth uſually purchaſe Goods, or Goods may be ſaid to purchaſe Money, is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be now examined, for we ought to conſider this matter, not according to ſuch remote reſpects, but as the caſe ſtands now amongſt our ſelves, and between us, and our Neighbours, and if it appear that Coyn is ſo neceſſary for our ſafety, that all the enjoyments we have will be in a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious condition without it, then it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it may deſerve to be eſteemed the moſt uſeful Treaſure in the Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34354:11"/>As Coyn is thus neceſſary for our defence, ſo is it likewiſe for the promoting of Trade and keeping up the value of Lands.</p>
            <p>Tho'a ſtock of Goods, and Credit, be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary as well as a ſtock of Money, for the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of Trade, yet ſeeing Credit depends upon an expectation of Coyn, and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring of Goods for Goods (if we ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to it) will not enable us to carry on Trade upon as advantageous terms as our Neighbours, therefore Coin will be alſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, not only as it is the Meaſure of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and Dealings, but as that which muſt ſupport Credit, and give the ſpring and life to Trade: Buyers muſt be enabled thereby, to purchaſe and pay for Goods, and Maſters to pay their Servants Wages, Merchants to pay Bills of Exchange, Freights, Seamens Wages, Cuſtoms and Charges. Plenty of Coin will not only quicken but force Trade, and as that may decreaſe ſo will this, the imployment of our People, the Gains of moſt Profeſſions whatſoever, and difficulties in all ſorts of Dealings will encreaſe upon us.</p>
            <p>That Lands were formerly at twelve years purchaſe, and are now at twenty, hath been chiefly attributed, and with good reaſon, to the encreaſe of our Coin, by Foreign Trade, for as that encreaſed, ſo Rents advanced, and Payments mended, and Purchaſers multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and bid one upon another, that they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34354:11"/>might be inſtated in what they deſir'd, for the ſame reaſons the want oſ Coyn muſt have the quite contrary effect, and occaſion the ill Payments of Rents, and ſink the value of Lands.</p>
            <p>If it be not agreed, That Gold and Silver is ſo uſeful for all theſe Ends, yet if it beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be eſteemed the <hi>Treaſure</hi> of a Nation, we ought to be carefull how we part with it, for corruptible Commodities, becauſe that will be a loſs and decreaſe of ſo much of its Riches.</p>
            <p>But what ought to make Gold and Silver yet more valuable, is the impoſſibility we ſhall be under, to ſupply the want of it by any other Species whatſoever.</p>
            <p>The Coining of Copper, Braſs, Tin, or Lead, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> however it may have ſerved for a turn, or for little Payments, hath been found by Experience, in all Countries where it hath been tryed, not to anſwer to the Value, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience or Uſe of Gold and Silver, and the advancing or debaſing of Coin, cannot be depended on to ſupply the want of it.</p>
            <p>Paper Credit will be ſo far from ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the want of Coin, that the want of Coin will ſtrike at the root, and ſoon deſtroy the uſe of that.</p>
            <p>Bills or Notes iſſued out by Bankers, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able on demand, may paſs for a Day, Week, or Month, and then ſometimes the Money
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34354:12"/>is taken out for them, or a new Note is made, which may again Circulate for a long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er time. But no perſons take any ſuch Notes, but on a ſuppoſition, that they will be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Coin, their Circulation depending entirely on an opinion, that Coin lies dead, ready to pay them when demanded: The leaſt ſuſpicion that there is not Coin in the Nation to diſcharge ſuch Notes, or that there will be a failure in the payment of them, when demanded, will occaſion a run for the Money, and put an end to the uſe of ſuch Notes, and if thoſe that have the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney upon which ſuch Notes are iſſued, do not make uſe of it, then ſuch Notes will be no more in effect, than a Circulation of Paper, inſtead of the Coin which lies dead, and if they do adventure to make uſe of it, then the Circulation of the Notes can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to no more than a preſent ſupply to them that iſſue them out, in the room of the Coin they have uſed, but not to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the want of Coin in the Nation, becauſe ſuch Notes muſt firſt or laſt be diſcharged by Coin, upon an expectation whereof, their Original, Exiſtence, and Credit depends.</p>
            <p>Truſting one another for ſome time, or time given for the payment of Goods bought, or Money borrowed upon Notes, made pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able at time, Bonds, or Mortgage, Deeds, which of late (to undervalue the uſe of Coin)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34354:12"/>have alſo been crowded in, under the Title of Paper Credit, as it hath been always ſo, it will ever be a great conveniency for the carrying on of Trade and Dealings, for as we never had a Stock of Coin ſufficient for all our occaſions, and what we have had is uſually upon Circulation, ſometimes in the hands of one man, and ſometimes in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's: Time is neceſſary for the drawing it in, or from one to another, or from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, or for mens valuing themſelves, on their Goods, Debts or Credit, but as ſuch Notes, Bonds or Mortgage Deeds, were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taken as a ſatisfaction of a debt but only as a ſecurity for the payment of Money, they can only be a ſupply to particular Perſons of their want of money, for ſome ſhort time, but not a ſupply to the want of Coin in the Nation, becauſe the uſe of ſuch Bills or Notes muſt be ſupported by Coin.</p>
            <p>Neither can it be expected, that Bills or Notes iſſued out upon Land ſecurity, ſhould Circulate, but upon a ſuppoſition, that Money may be had for them, on demand: when that fails, tho' the Land ſettled be valuable, and well ſecured, the Credit of ſuch Bills will fail alſo, becauſe ſuch Bills cannot anſwer all mens occaſions or humours, ſome will be afraid of diſputes and contingencies that may happen in getting the Poſſeſſion of ſuch Lands: and others will be unwilling to be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34354:13"/>involv'd with a Multitude in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch ſmall ſhares, as they may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled to, when ſuch Bills are diſperſt over the Nation: If Truſtees be appointed by the ſettlement, to ſell ſuch Lands upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of payment, yet doubts will ariſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will act or deal fairly in ſelling and making diviſions, and if they do, and the Eſtate be ſold and Bills paid, then after all, it will confirm the uſe of Coin, as alſo beſt for payment of debts, becauſe it can be divided and aſcertained, and that Paper Credit can only be of uſe to gain time for payment, but that it cannot ſupply the want of Coyn in the Nation, it being little leſs than a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction in it ſelf, that the want of Coin ſhould be ſupplied by Paper Credit, if there cannot be any ſuch Credit without Coin.</p>
            <p>How far ſuch Notes or Bills may be a help to the carrying on of Trade, or inſtrumental to encreaſe and multiply Trade and Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or to give a quick diſpatch in making payments, or how it may ſerve by chance, or for a turn, or in caſe of a neceſſity, or how far a falſe Coin (if it paſs) may help to carry on Trade and Dealings as well as Paper, if it be not anſwered with Coin, is not neceſſary to be examined, what has been ſaid not being intended to hinder any good uſe that can be made of them, for the getting
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34354:13"/>of Money, but to rectifie miſtakes that may occaſion the conſumption of the Coin we have, and make ſuch Paper Credit uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, or to force us upon a neceſſity to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on Artificial Treaſure, which in Caſes of exigencies, may probably fail: Let us rather keep our Coyn, and depend on that which cannot fail.</p>
            <p>The intrinſick value which Gold and Silver hath in its own nature, the general eſteem given to it by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Nations and the long Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence all have had of the uſefulneſs of it, muſt in all reaſon give it a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to all Paper Credit; Bills or Notes can only be made valuable, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>among our ſelves, and that muſt be by ſome conſequential or relative Vertue, annext by Art, or force, which tho never ſo well contrived, will be liable to ſome Objections, for want of that intrinſick va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, which Gold and Silver carrys in it ſelf, and the more force may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, the more miſchief will attend it, for that will occaſion the hoarding up, or the Exportation of the Coin we have, cauſe Complaints of Invaſion of Property, or changing mens Securitys or Eſtates, into Paper without their own conſent; and give as much oppoſition to the currency of them,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34354:14"/>as if they carried Poyſon wrapt up in them, which if it do not deſtroy the uſe of Paper Credit and truſt in Dealing, will be, but taking off a burden from Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, to put it on the preſent Creditors, for ſuch Bills will be at a full-ſtop, when they come to the hands of a perſon not Indebted. And ſeeing the late Exchequer Bills which had ſo great a priviledge an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex'd them, as to paſs to the King's Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at the Exchequer, and to be taken in all payments for Taxes, or Debts due to the King, have not always paſt in time of Peace, at <hi>par,</hi> What then may be expected from any kind of Paper Credit, in caſe of an Exigency, or preſſing Occaſion, for a greater Priviledge than what was given to the Exchequer Bills cannot well be invented.</p>
            <p>All arguments for diſcrediting the uſe and value of Coin, and to perſuade us that Paper Credit will ſupply the want of it, as they may occaſion a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Exportation of what we have, and make us careleſs in getting of more, appear much like the Methods Practiſed by thoſe that have a mind to make a prey of ſome young Heir, firſt they perſwade him, that his Money will do him no good, nor be any Comfort to him, if he keep it by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34354:14"/>him, next that he is Rich, and his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate inexhauſtible, and that he need not fear any want, becauſe all that he can ſpend will be ſoon ſupplied from his Lands, or Incomes, and when they have thus wrought him up into a careleſs and expenſive temper, and got ſome ſhare of his Eſtate and Wealth, if Money do not come in as faſt as he may have occaſion for it, than they perſwade him to make uſe of Paper Credit, Bonds, Judgments, or Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages, for the ſtopping of clamours and demands, and to ſupport him in his Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious way of living.</p>
            <p>There is ſo near a reſemblance between the circumſtances of private Families com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with each other, and the affairs of a Nation compared with another Nation, that thoſe that have not time to conſider all the Circumſtances that may be neceſſary to make a Judgment, what ought to be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the moſt uſefull Treaſure of a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or how Nations may grow Rich or be Impoveriſhed, may yet make a Concluſion by their obſervations on Families, or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons, and if it appear, that Lands, Houſes, Jewels, Furniture, Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page, or what elſe particular Perſons may eſteem and value as their Riches, will be in danger to be taken from them, for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34354:15"/>the payment of their Debts, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſuch Paper Credit (tho' happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the beſt that can be invented,) if they do not make a Proviſion of Coin to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it, ſo will the Glory, Welfare, and Riches of this Nation be in like danger without Coin to unite our Strength, and make it ſerviceable for our defence.</p>
            <p>If upon theſe Conſiderations it appear that Coin is the moſt uſefull Treaſure of a Nation, as well for the Body Politick as for the uſe of particular Perſons, then it will follow that great care ought to be taken for the retaining of what we have, and gaining of more, for tho' it be of ſo great Importance, yet nothing is more likely to creep upon us inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and not be perceived till felt, Than the want of Coin, therefore, tho' we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee with our Eyes, how it is carryed from us, becauſe a great value may lie in a little room, yet we ſhould endeavour to diſcover it by making a judgment on Cauſes and Effects, and as it may inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly decreaſe, ſo it will not be regain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without great difficulties and length of time; What Quantities other Nations have, or how we are provided in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with our Neighbours, is not eaſie to be computed, but if while they are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34354:15"/>uſing all endeavours by their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Commerce, and Edicts relating to Trade, and otherwiſe, to preſerve and encreaſe what they have, we ſhould be miſlead by erreneous Principles and Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, to decreaſe ours, we may give them ſuch an advantage, as may not be retrieved hereafter, and Repent when it may be too late.</p>
            <p>It is a common Maxim, that what ſeems true to ſome, may at leaſt be allowed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, what is believed by moſt, to be a further degree of probability, but what has the approbation of general conſent and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, carries with it one of the greateſt Evidences any thing is capable off, and tis little leſs than pure Arrogance and Folly for any ſingle perſon to prefer his <hi>own Judgment</hi> before the general ſuffrage of mankind.</p>
            <p>That Gold and Silver were always had in great eſteem, is manifeſt by ancient Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, and as the converting it into Coin, made it more uſeful, ſo likewiſe more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable by all Nations.</p>
            <p>The Author of the Eſſay on Ways and Means, being of a different opinion as to the Uſe and Ualue of Coin, After having expreſt his reſentment in the firſt Leaf of his aforementioned Book, againſt a certain perſon that had made a doubt, whether
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34354:16"/>all extended Traffick inriched the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and had diſcover'd the Vanity of his Thoughts in pretending to compute all manner of Expences, Conſumptions, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portations, and Importations, in diſtinct Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, as well as in his opinions upon Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects relating to Trade, Luxury, and Gold, and Silver; He comes to the matter, for which it is ſuppoſed, his Book was chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſign'd, <hi>viz.</hi> to under value the Uſe of Coin, that no ſtop may be put to the Exportation of it, and therein to reflect upon thoſe that are of a contrary Opinion, picking out for thoſe purpoſes ſome Words and parts of Paragraphs in a little tract in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled, <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Eaſt-India inconſiſtent in their Manufacture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the method he has taken, to make room for his Reflections, by picking out Words out of ſome Paragraphs, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out Words in others, quoting what is not to be found in the Book, and perverting the ſenſe of other Paragraphs quite contrary to their true meaning, is diſingenious, ſo his taking no notice of ſome whole Pages, ought to be reckon'd a piece of Art, to conceal the truth from his Reader, this therefore has made it neceſſary that the whole Paragraphs upon which he builds his Reflections ſhould be here recited at large.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:34354:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> inconſiſtent in their Manufacturies.</head>
               <p>Page 6. <hi>But before any argument ſhould be enter'd upon which of theſe accounts is moſt juſtifiable, it is requiſite to agree up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on matter of Fact and Principles, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly what may be called the Riches or Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of a Nation, or what may be eſteemed the moſt uſeful, after what is abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, to ſupply the neceſſities of Nature, ſome being of Opinion, that nothing deſerves that name or to be ſo eſteemed,, but Gold and Silver; becauſe no other Metal is ſo laſting and durable, or ſo fit to receive the Royal Stamp, nor to be aſcertained in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, and divided into ſeveral denominations, nor ſo convenient to pay Fleets and Armies, and becauſe it has a general eſteem in all parts of</hi> Europe, <hi>as fit for ſuch uſes, and to be the Standard for the carrying on of Commerce, and to be bartered off for all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Commoàities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Jewels, Lead, Tin or Iron, though durable, yet having not thoſe other qualiſicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, do not ſo well deſerve to be eſteemed Treaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Author picks out of theſe Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphs the words he thought moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for his purpoſe, and then aſſerts.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:34354:17"/>Page the 16. <hi>That in truth Money is at bottom no more than the Counters with which Men in their dealings have been accuſtomed to reckon. Suppoſe the</hi> Hollanders <hi>ſhould lend to ſome foreign State upon Jewels, or the pledge of cautionary Towns, two thirds of all their Species, would they ceaſe upon ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be a wealthy People; moſt certainly not, and ſuch a ſecurity put into their hands, will be real and true Riches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Page the 62. <hi>Gold and Silver are often a ſurfiting Dyet to a Nation, and there may be as well too much as too little of this kind of Treaſure, if not turned to proper uſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where it flows in ſo faſt as to choak indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, or where it is ſuffered to Stagnate, it doth more hurt than good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Page 64. <hi>Theſe Metals then are ſo far from being as our Author would have it, the only or moſt uſeful Riches, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they may be hurtful, and never at all uſeful, but when in motion, and miniſtring to Trade, and the other buſineſs of a People,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Treaſure therefore accidentally flowing in, interupts and choaks this Induſtry, may be prejudicial to the Publick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not probable that theſe Aſſertions would have been publiſhed in a Book written with ſo much deliberation, but
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34354:17"/>that the Author was at a great loſs how to depreciate the uſe of Coin, and value of Gold and Silver, that we might be negligent of what we have, and careleſs in endeavouring to get more.</p>
               <p>Counters are uſually made of Ebony, Paper, Paſteboard, or of any baſe metal; Coin of the moſt valuable, when Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are uſed to keep Accounts or Reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onings, it is to determine what may be owing from one perſon to another, in order to demand Coin for Payment, which in all Parts is taken in diſcharge of Debts, and here with us preſcribed by Law, to be taken in diſcharge of all Specialities or Debts whatſoever.</p>
               <p>If Money be no more valuable than Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which Men uſe only to reckon by, that it ſhould have a general eſteem with all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that there ſhould be ſuch contending for it, who ſhall get moſt, and that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould of late years be executed for adulterating and clipping of it, is unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable.</p>
               <p>The inſtance there given, makes not for his purpoſe, for tho it ſhould be, that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> do purchaſe their Jewels for two thirds of their Specie, which may deſerve to be eſteem'd Wealth, yet not having their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue aſcertained, nor being capable to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34354:18"/>into ſeveral denominations, they would not probabley be ſo uſeful for their defence, or carrying on of their Trade, as Money.</p>
               <p>But if inſtead of this, he had given an Inſtance, when the <hi>Dutch,</hi> bought Jewels or Cautionary Towns with Counters, it ſhould have been allowed as a good proof of his Aſſertion.</p>
               <p>Tho Coin is that which paſſes from had to hand in Dealings, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (it may be ſaid) it is much uſed as a pledge, yet ſtill not as Counters to reckon by, becauſe it is always taken as a Satisfaction and Payment: The deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of Pounds Shillings and Pence, may reſemble the uſe of Counters; but the Inſtance the Author gives, makes out, that he would not have this aſſertion ſo underſtood, and the expreſſions <hi>page</hi> 62. and 64, do confirm, that the Author is of opinion that Money ought not to be regarded more than as Counters to reckon by, which it is probable is grounded, on the ſemilitude and reſemblance, which our new Money has to ſome Counters.</p>
               <p>It naturally follows that when things are of no ſolid uſe, and of little value, and that dangers attend the having or keeping of them, that all perſons will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and deſpiſe ſuch, and have no regard
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34354:18"/>for them and approve of a laviſh Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>It is apparent to every one that we are not in danger at preſent, to be ſurfeited with Gold or Silver, or to have ſo much as to choak Induſtry, or too much for neceſſary uſes, therefore whether theſe and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Notions in that Book, which have ſuch a tendency to make us careleſs how to diſpoſe of our Coyn, and to incline us to turn our real Treaſure into what is but Artificial, and Fictitious, or to exchange it for Gugas and Toys, are proper to be diſperſed at this time, the State of the Nation being conſider'd in reference to our Trade, Debts, Paper-Credit, and Defence is left to better Judgments.</p>
               <p>But ſince this Author has publiſhed <hi>page</hi> 432, <hi>That he has offered himſelf to go for the</hi> Indias <hi>with an honeſt deſign, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on principles that reſpect the Kingdoms ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> it is hoped that if our Coin be at bottom, no more than Counters to reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with (ſeeing he may find Pebbles there for that uſe) that he will endeavour to prevent the carrying out of Coin, or Gold and Silver, in the Squadron that may Tranſport him to <hi>India,</hi> which as it would give great ſatisfaction to ſome of his Friends he may leave behind him, ſo
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34354:19"/>it would prevent the danger of giving the <hi>Indians</hi> a ſurfeit, or choaking their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, and making his Voyage ineffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, ſo well deſigned for the Kingdoms good, but if that ſhould meet oppoſition, then that he would leave us a Scheme, (leaſt our Coin ſhould grow ſcarce) how to put in practice what he has aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted.</p>
               <p>Page 165. <hi>Tho Money has hitherto been called the meaſure of Trade, yet mankind may agree to ſet up any thing elſe in its room; and whatever it be, in the place where it univerſally takes, it may ſerve their turn as well as Gold and Silver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ſuppoſed this may be taken as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Argument for the diſcrediting the uſe and value of Coin; but it would have carried more weight with it, if the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor had told us, what this other thing ſhould be, and how the various intereſts of Nations ſhould be reconiled, and what probability there is, that all makind will agree in it, or that any ſuch Project would univerſally take; but that none of his good Notions may be loſt for want of endeavours to reduce them to practiſe, and becauſe the <hi>Great Mogull</hi> ought to come in (as a part of mankind) for a Confedrate in this Affair, as well as all trading Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34354:19"/>If while he is upon his Imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>India,</hi> he can find means to adjuſt it with that Prince, that no more of our Coin may be carried to thoſe parts, as it would be a good foundation for ſetling this new Meaſure of Trade, ſo he may juſtly expect that it ſhould be reckoned as an addition to the great Services he may probably accompliſh in this Voyage, for the Kingdoms good.</p>
               <p>But tho Money be no more at botome than Counters to reckon with in this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Opinion, <hi>Page</hi> 16. yet <hi>Page</hi> 101. <hi>He ſays that the Species of Money is the life of Trade.</hi> Page 170. <hi>Moey is the Foundation of Credit, where there is none there can be no Credit.</hi> Page 171. <hi>That to ſupport Credit it is neceſsary that there be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance: That there ſhall be kept in the Kingdom a ſufficient quantity of the Species to turn in Trade, in the payment of Taxes and Rents; and in the Manufactures to keep the Wheels of the Machine in motion.</hi> And Page 7.15. <hi>That Gold and Silver is the meaſure of Trade.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe expreſſions give ſome hopes that the Author will in time agree, that Coin is alſo neceſſary for the Defence of the Nation, and more uſeful than Counters to reckon with, unleſs he find it impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34354:20"/>to retract his opinion, becauſe it is not a chance expreſſion, but offered as his judgment, backt with reflections, in oppoſition to what had been aſſerted in the little Tract he mentions, <hi>That Gold and Silver is the only, or moſt uſeful Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Nation</hi> but if he cannot alter his opinion, that he would then in ſuch caſe reconcile his own Opinions, about Coin, and explain his Objections made againſt Coin, by giving an account what other Treaſure there is, or ever was in the Nation more uſeful, or by which we have had any greater advantage, if not turned to proper uſes, or ever was fitter for Circulation, miniſtering to Trade, and the other buſineſs of the People, <hi>then Coin,</hi> and what danger we are in at this time to be ſurfeited with it, and how he will reconcile ſuch Opinions with <hi>Xenophon,</hi> mentioned in a Diſcourſe upon improving the State of <hi>Athens,</hi> Printed as an addition to his, Part 1. P. 23. <hi>A Maſter of a Family indeed when he is well provided with Furniture and Houſhold Goods, buys no more; but no man was ever ſo over-ſtock'd with Silver, as not to deſire a further encreaſe, if there are any who have more than their occaſions require,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34354:20"/>they hoard up the reſt, with as much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as if they actually made uſe of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And when a Nation is in a flouriſhing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, no one is at a loſs how to imploy his Money, the men lay it out in fine Armor and in magnificent Houſes and Buildings; Women lay it out in great Equipage, coſtly Habits and rich Cloaths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And in accidents of War when our Lands lie Fallow and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncultivated, or in a publick Dearth, and Scarcity, what reſerves have we left to apply to, but Silver, to purchaſe neceſſaries for Subſtance, or hire Auxiliaries for our Defence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If it is objected that Gold is as uſefull as Silver, I will not diſpute it, but this I am ſure off, that plenty of Gold always lowered its value and advanced the price of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have inſiſted the longer on theſe general Reflections to encourage adventurers of all kinds to employ as many hands as pſſible in ſo advantagious a Trade, from theſe plain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations that Mines can never be exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nor can Silver loſe its va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon which Diſcourſe of <hi>Zenophon</hi>'s it may be obſerved that he was of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p>That a Nation could not have too much Silver.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:34354:21"/>That it would be uſeful as a defence for a Nation againſt the accidents of War or in caſe of a Famine, to purchaſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries.</p>
               <p>That Gold was not ſo uſefull as Silver.</p>
               <p>That Silver could never loſe its Value.</p>
               <p>If the Author's Expreſſions, <hi>P.</hi> 101.170, 171. muſt be taken as a Concurrence with <hi>Zenophon</hi>'s Opinion; and that his aſſertion, That Money is at bottom no more than Counters, a choaking and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting Commodity may be juſtified, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe being money Generally paſſes in exchange for other Commodities, That therefore it has the Nature of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, and may ſurfeit as well as others, and that it is not a contradiction to his other Expreſſions, yet if his ability to make ſuch diſtinctions had been reſerved for ſome other Subject, in which the Safety and Welfare of the Nation had been leſs concern'd, it would be more al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable, for if by ſuch infinuations, we ſhould be miſlead to be careleſs in what refers to our Coyn, and longer permit a laviſh Exportation according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Book, and be thereby redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a want: ſuch inſipid Niceties will make us no amends for the great preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice we ſhall receive thereby.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:34354:21"/>The Second Propoſition, <hi>That tho moſt Trades afford great conveniencies and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, yet that it is difficult to get Treaſure from foreign Natious, by Trade, and that we have diminiſhed and not increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our. Treaſure, ſince the year</hi> 1666 <hi>by fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Trade.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tho it be hardly poſſible to pry into all the myſteries of Trade, and to give a true account of the ſeveral turnings and windings, ſteps and degrees, and progreſs of every particular Trade, yet by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring into the Foundation and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of Trade in general, and into the State of our Coin, or what elſe among us is eſteemed Wealth or Treaſure, and alſo by diſtinguiſhing what has been gotten by the Product of our Annual Crops, and Labour at Home, and what acquired by our foreign Trade, and by a due conſideration of what Trades may really enrich or elſe impoveriſh a Nation, and how the Treaſure of the Kingdom may be waſted and conſumed by Trades, which yet may bring great gain to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons. It may appear how diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34354:22"/>it is to get Treaſure from foriegners; and in what proportion it has been got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by ſuch foreign Traffick: From all which ſome uſeful obſervations may be drawn for the directing of Trade for the future, that ſo we may not only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and improve the advantage and conveniences we at preſent enjoy by our Trade, but may likewiſe by our more prudent Negotiations, augment the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Wealth of the whole Body Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick.</p>
               <p>Now as on the one ſide thoſe opinions that all Trades or extended Traffick do bring in what may well be eſteemed an addition of Treaſure, and that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fail of geting it by ſuch Trade, may induce us to allow and encourage thoſe Trades that will conſume the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure we have, or may divert us from taking right methods to gain more. So the undervaluing the advantages we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by Trade may occaſion a remiſſneſs to preſerve and ſecure thoſe Trades we are in poſſeſſion of, and hinder the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying our endeavours to advance and improve them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:34354:22"/>An enquiry therefore to find out by what methods this Nation may get or loſe by Trade, and what diſtinctions may be made between the conveniencies ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruing by Trade, and the gaining of Treaſure; and between the gains of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, and the gains of a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will not only be of uſe in all conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations refering to Trade; but alſo to diſcover that the conveniences and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages we have by Trade, are of ſo great importance, that the care of the Government will be well applyed to improve and incourage all Trades, that do not conſume our Treaſure, tho no addition to the Treaſure of the Nation could be expected to be gotten from fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners by them.</p>
               <p>The Conſumption of ſuch of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts as we cannot ſpend at home, the procuring from foreign Parts in return of them, what we want for the ſupply of our neceſſities, or to be improved by a further Manufacture, or to be rendered uſeful for the defence of the Nation: the increaſe of Ships or Seamen by the imployments given by our Exports and Imports: The ſupport of great numbers who have their ſole dependance on Trade for their livelihoods, and the incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34354:23"/>that is given thereby to the multiplying of our People, and to Induſtry, by the expectation of gains to all thoſe that have any part in the management of it, are advantages ſo extenſive, that abſtracted from the expectation of gaining Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to the Nation from foreigners, they may well deſerve to be eſteemed as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the Body Politick as Blood to the Body Natural.</p>
               <p>Moſt of the advantages that attend Trade, and gains to the perſons that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it on, are the natural conſequences of Trade, no Nation would allow, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a Trade with another Nation, nor encourage it among themſelves, if they did not find ſome conveniency or advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by it, and it cannot be expected that the particular perſons that ingage in it, ſhould imploy their time and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes that way, if they were not indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thereto by an expectation of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit:</p>
               <p>But the gaining of Treaſure from fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Nations will not appear to be a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural conſequence, ariſing from the Bulk of Trade, nor to be procured, or obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without Art, and a prudent manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the advantages we have by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which in many caſes will need the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34354:23"/>help of the Government; for all Nations under well conſtituted Governments, are vigilant and careful to preſerve what they eſteem their Treaſure, and in their Councils adviſe and concert, how to reſtrain and diſcourage ſuch Trades as they ſuſpect will exhauſt their Wealth, not willingly permitting to any foreigners that advantage, whether the methods taken for that end have been effective or not, is not now the queſtion, they are ſtill at liberty to change their means, as they ſee cauſe, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> who above all Nations, are beſt ſupplyed with Gold and Silver, and have been moſt negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in Concerns relating to Trade, yet by an eſtabliſht Law, it was a Capital Crime (till of late) for any perſon to Export it, that they might keep thoſe Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to themſelves; and others have taken and do obſerve a more infallible method to ſecure their Treaſure, by good Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry in the Conſumption of foreign Comodities at Home, ſending to other Countries what they Import from abroad, as well as what they can ſpare of their own Products and Manufactures, to which they give all encouragement, that they may export much, and Import little to be conſumed at home.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:34354:24"/>The Bulk or greateſt part of our fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Trade, hath been uſually carryed on by Exportation of our Woollen Goods, and other Manufactures, Fiſh, Lead, Tin, Coals, Hides and Proviſions, and by the Importation of Timber, Deals, Pitch, Hemp, Tarr, Iron, Wine, Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Salt, Oyl, Reaiſins, Currants, Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen-Cloath, Paper, wrought Silks, Druggs, and by our Plantation-goods Imported and Exported, all which may amount to Nine parts in Ten of our foreign Trade, as well in Bulk as in Value: Yet when our Trade in theſe Goods, is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on to an equality, and we take from another Nation in Goods to be conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at home, to the full value of what they take from us, ſuch Trades are ſo far from bringing us in Treaſure, that they ſignifie no more than ſending to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Country to be conſumed, the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus we had over and above what was neceſlary for our own Expence, which would have periſhed at home, or have been of no uſe, if they had not been Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported. And the Woollen Goods, or what elſe we ſent out, would as well have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to be eſteemed the Riches of the Nation, if they had been kept at home, as the Fruit, Wine, Sugar, or Tobaco
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34354:24"/>brought in return of them, but tho ſuch Trades carried on in equality, are in effect like bartering Goods for Goods, and we cannot by them get from foreign Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, any addition of Gold or Silver, or what elſe may in ſtrictneſs deſerve to be eſteemed the Treaſure of the Nation; yet when carried on by the exportation of our Product, or Goods purchaſed with them, ſuch Trades afford great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, and give a great encouragement to all ſorts of Improvements, by this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption Abroad, added to our conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at Home; for the Landed Men, have thereby opportunities to ſell more of their Products, and encouragement to Manure more of their Lands, to encreaſe working in Mines, and to build Houſes in hopes to advance their incomes, the Manufactures to work upon, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove ſuch Products and Materials to the higheſt Perfection, the Buyers, Sellers and Traders in ſuch Commodities, and the labouring men, that give their help to the carrying on of ſuch Trades, by taking and curing of Fiſh, working in Mines, or otherwiſe, are hereby enabled to live and to purchaſe, and conſume the Products of the Earth, which is alſo a further advantage to the Landed Men;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34354:25"/>The Ships and Seamen, in which the ſafety of the Nation is particularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, are thereby preſerved, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by the imployments which ſuch Trades afford them, when carried on by our own Ships. All which Trades as they have their original from the natural pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts of the Earth and Sea, their improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the labour and induſtry of our People; their ſpring from an expectation of gain to particular perſons, their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from the circulation of the Coin, as the principal and moſt neceſſary inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or wheels to keep it in motion. So they have a tendency to the multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of people, in which the ſtrength of the Nation doth much conſiſt, to the increaſe of Riches to particular perſons, which in many reſpects may be eſteemed the Wealth of the Nation, and to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing for us what we want from abroad, without conſuming our Coin, which would lie dead, and be of little benefit to us, nor the labour of our people, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch Trades, and when in the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of ſuch Trades we put off cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Goods for Goods more durable, laſting and ſerviceable for better purpoſes then the Nation may alſo have a further advantage.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:34354:25"/>Tho it be a queſtion whether our having good materials, well manufactured, be the cauſe of Trade, or Trade the cauſe of improving and manufacturing our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials; yet it being plain, that one has a dependance on the other, and that by the labour of our people Lands are improved, and Materials advanced in value, (ſome from 100 <hi>l,</hi> to 1000 <hi>l,</hi> or more) and that ſuch Goods whether ſold for Exportation or kept at home are eſteemed according to thoſe values, therefore what ever additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on has been made to the Wealth of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by ſuch Materials ſo improved, and the improvements of any foreign Materials; ought to be attributed to our labour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, &amp; not as gotten by foreign Traffick.</p>
               <p>The gaining of Treaſure from foreigners or by foreign Traffick, ſignifies the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Nation ſome Species and Commodities, valuable, durable, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to be uſeful and ſerviceable to the Nation or Body Politick.</p>
               <p>Tho when we get Gold or Silver or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther durable Species in exchange of our periſhable Commodities ſent out, it may be reckoned as treaſure gotten by foreign traffick, yet the original of ſuch riches is our products and labour, becauſe Gold and Silver is procured in exchange for ſuch goods ſent out.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:34354:26"/>As we cannot get Treaſure by the bulk of our foreign Trade, ſo it can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly change hands by that part of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick Trade, which conſiſts in buying and ſelling amongſt our ſelves, and in mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of handicraft Wares, or Goods, for our own uſe; but tho our Treaſure can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be encreaſed by ſuch Trades, yet they alſo afford great conveniences, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Corporations are chiefly ſupported by them, Families ſupplyed with what they want, and the encreaſe of people encouraged by the livelihood, ſuch Trades afford to great numbers: And by that part of our Domeſtick Trade, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on improving and manufacturing the products of the Earth and Sea, we have yet much greater advantages ariſing from the labour of our people, by making ſuch products uſeful, and by augmenting their value, by which we are not only ſtor'd with ſuch Commodities as may be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Riches and neceſſary to ſerve our own occaſions, but alſo provided to ſend ſuch abroad, as may procure us Treaſure from foreign Nations.</p>
               <p>And by ſuch Trades we have alſo a farther conveniency, by the Revenues le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied by Cuſtoms, and Exciſe, for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the publick charge of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34354:26"/>which when laid on ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities as may be Imported, in return of our products, and in ſuch manner, as that they may be a means to encourage good Trades, and diſcourage bad; they have been found to be eaſie, equal, and convenient, all which advantages do na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ariſe, or may be had from Trades carried on by the Exportation of Goods of our own growth, and in ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion by the goods of the growth of any other Country, if ſuch be procured in return of our own products ſent out, and ſuch Trades ought alſo to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, becauſe they cannot do us any hurt, and have a firm foundation, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſupply we may have of ſuch goods from within our ſelves.</p>
               <p>But as theſe advantages may be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from Trades carried on by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of our goods, ſo great incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies may be feared from Trades carried on by the Exportation of our Coin or Bullion; for inſtead of yielding any advantages by the Exportation, ſuch carry from us, what was moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to give Spring and Life to all our Trades, and was in it ſelf more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable as to the Nation, than what is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually brought in return of it, and being
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:34354:27"/>we have not any Mines of Gold or Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Trades that are carried on by the Exportation of it, cannot have a ſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence; for if little ſhould be Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which may be feared from the languiſhing ſtate of our good Trades, and we ſhould not have plenty of Coin at home, (which ſuch a free and large Exportation may in few years occaſion), we ſhall ſee an end of ſuch Trades, and be at a great loſs how to be reinſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in thoſe which had a good Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Gold and Silver, has ſo great an eſteem in moſt parts, above all Commodities (thoſe excepted that may be wanted for the ſupport of Life, or abſolutely neceſſary for the defence of a Nation) that nothing can make amends to a Nation for Bullion exported, but Bullion imported, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the exportation of it ſhould not be here permitted, unleſs we could be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that it ſhould be brought in with an increaſe, by the ſame trades that carried it out; for tho particular perſons may make great advantages by ſending it out, becauſe by its being ſo eſteemed, they may obtain what goods they pleaſe for it, without loſs of time, and that ſuch trades may for a time give an imployment
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34354:27"/>to ſome Ships; yet when periſhable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities are brought in return of it, and conſumed at home, ſo much of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Nation muſt be diminiſhed, as was ſent out to purchaſe ſuch Goods, for which no ſufficient recompence can be made, by ſuch temporary, and private advantages; ſuch exportations may be good to buy Trade for the advantage of the particular Men concerned in it, but not to procure Treaſure for the Nation.</p>
               <p>If Coin be the Life of Trade, the chief ſupport of Credit, ſo neceſſary for our Defence and Safety and that all Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and Domeſtick Imployments have ſo great a dependence upon the circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, as has been inſtanced; then the Arguments uſually given, that it is as much for our advantage to export it for Trade, as any other Commodity ought not to be allowed, becauſe it is ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for our Safety, and for the ſupport of Trades, and Profeſſions at home, above all other Commodities, that all will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer if there be a ſcarcity of it; and as the ſending it out to purchaſe goods has ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded much to our other importations; ſo by ſome of the goods brought in, our exportations of more profitable goods have been leſſened, and the conſumption of our
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:34354:28"/>Manufactures at home diminiſhed, the gaining of Gold and Silver being that which upon an examination will appear to be, what is chiefly meant by the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Treaſure from foreigners by Trade; the ſending it out again, amounts to a ſpending, or giving it away, aſſoon as got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, to get Treaſure from foreigners by Trade, the Nation muſt act like Uſurers, part with no more of their Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver than their neceſſary occaſions require, unleſs upon good Security or aſſurance that it ſhall be repaid them with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</p>
               <p>Tho no trades would be driven for any long time, that did not make ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns of profit to thoſe that are concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them, and it may therefore be ſaid, that all trades are in ſome ſort advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous, or profitable, yet from thence to infer that all trade or extended traffick enriches the Nation, is a wide ſtep, for ſome Trades may bring gain to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons, which yet may conſume and be deſtructive of the treaſure of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>No true eſtimate can be made of any foreign trade with reſpect to the Nation in general, unleſs Conſumption (in which all trade in Commodities muſt terminate)
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:34354:28"/>be conſidered as a part of Trade, and as that upon which getting or loſing by Trade has its chief dependance, tho' the landed Man may make up his Accounts aſſoon as he has ſold his Products, the Manufacturer aſſoon as he has ſold his Manufacture; the Merchant as ſoon as he has ſold, what he may bring from abroad in return of what he ſent out; and the Shopkeeper, aſſoon as he has ſold to the Conſumer, what he has bought of the Merchant, yet ſuch Computations can only diſcover what gain has been made by particular perſons in thoſe ſteps, and progreſs, which Trade has taken, and not what gains has accrued to the Nation, which can only be adjuſted upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion or making up of an Account, of the whole Trade, or conſidering it from the firſt Buyer to the laſt Vendor; for as none of the particular Trades can make a judgment whether they have got or loſt, till they have ſold their Goods, which is as conſumption to them; ſo no exact Account can be made, whether a Nation get or loſe by any Trade without taking in Conſumption; whereby it may be known how the ſaid Goods are finally diſpoſed off; every ſale is an alteration of property, and as ſuch, is a Conſumption
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34354:29"/>to the ſeveral Buyers and Sellers, but the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions property and concern ſtill remains in ſuch Goods till they are really and actually conſumed.</p>
               <p>A Trade carried on by the importation of ſuch Commodities, which ſerve only to luxury, may be as advantageous to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as any other, if ſuch Commodities be again exported and conſumed abroad, and durable Goods brought in the room of them, goods purchaſed with Bullion ſent out, if re-exported and we receive by the product of them, more Bullion than we ſent out, may likewiſe afford gains to the Nation, but if ſuch Goods be conſumed at home, it will have a quite contrary effect. 'Tis not the private gain of particular Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders here among us, that doth neceſſarily increaſe the Publick Treaſure, but this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes from the Species or ſorts of Goods imported, being the ſubject of that Trade, as if it be Silver or Gold or durable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities that are brought in: Theſe, though they are ſold and transferred from one hand to another, yet ſtill remain as a durable Stock in the Nation, but if the Traffick conſiſt of periſhable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, tho' the Traders may get, that bring them in, and theſe through whoſe hands they paſs, yet if conſumed at home,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34354:29"/>home, they cannot make any Addition to the Treaſure of the Nation.</p>
               <p>Therefore in order to compute the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions gain by any Trade, we muſt exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and know, not only of what was ſent out, but alſo of what was brought in, and how conſumed, if Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver or durable Commodities deſerving the name of Treaſure, be brought in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of periſhable Commodities ſent out, then it may be concluded that the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gets; but on the contrary, if periſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Commodities be brought in and ſpent at home, procured by Gold and Silver or durable Commodities ſent out, then the Nation muſt loſe, which cannot be known unleſs conſumption be conſider'd as a part of Trade, that the periſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Commodities may be diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from thoſe that may remain to the Nation, as a laſting durable ſtock, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Name of Treaſure, and if all dealings from the firſt buyer to the laſt vender may be properly called <hi>Trade</hi> then to make Computations of <hi>the Trade, of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, or whether the Nation have got or loſt by any particular Trade, without tracing the conſumption of the Goods brought in, ſo far as the laſt vender, is ont only contrary to the method that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34354:30"/>ſhould be taken to make a true compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; but alſo contrary to the meaning of the word as it refers to the Nation: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the conſumption of Goods in the hands of the laſt vender, be in ſtrictneſs of words a part of Trade, or only an Appendix is not worth diſputing; for by the laſt ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it may be diſcover'd what is become of the Goods, and in this caſe the word <hi>Trade</hi> ought to be taken in the largeſt ſenſe of Negation.</p>
               <p>Tho' it may be preſumed, that in the infancy and firſt beginning of Trade, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more was deſigned than to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure natural Conveniencies by a permu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Commodities, yet ſince the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Gold, Silver and Induſtry, it is obvious, that all Trading Nations have applied their thoughts, ſome how to gain Treaſure from Foreign Nations, and others how to preſerve what they had, which, and how to inlarge their Trade by bartering of Goods, have been the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the great ſtruglings, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts, we have ſeen about Trade, and the various methods Nations have taken to theſe Ends.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:34354:30"/>As this Kingdom is advantageouſly Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated, well ſtored with Natural Products and with people Skill'd in artificial im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements, ſo it muſt be our own fault if we do not make Trade as beneficial to us, as it is to any other Nation, and particularly as it relates to the gaining of Treaſure from Foreigners, but it is as improbable, we ſhould get ſuch Treaſure without agreeing upon methods that may be proper for thoſe ends, and a Vigilant care to obſerve and purſue them, as that a Maſter of a Family ſhould grow rich that leaves all his concerns to the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Servants: For if Induſtry be neglected, and Luxury promoted, it will have the ſame effect in the concerns of a Nation, as the Profuſeneſs or ill Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry of Servants will have with the Maſter of a Family.</p>
               <p>Tho Trade was always Subject to great Variations and Changes, occaſion'd either by Laws and Regulations, made by Princes and States, or by the increaſe or decreaſe of People, Ingenuity, or Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, or by an alteration in the Humours, Judgment, or Intereſt of the Conſumers, upon which Trade, ever had its great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt dependance, yet few inſtances can be given, when any Trading Nation did ſo
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34354:31"/>far miſtake their Intereſt, as to concur in ſuch Variations or Notions, as had a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to a quite contrary effect to what they deſign'd and expected.</p>
               <p>The Trade of this Kingdom was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, when the value of our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports conſiſted moſt in Wool unwrought, and we had few Manufactures. By the ſteps which our Anceſtors took to make it more advantageous, it appears, that they thought it their true Intereſt, that all endeavours ſhould be uſed to eſtabliſh and improve the Manufacturing of Goods at home, and promote their Conſumption: and that Foreign Trade ſhould be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on, by the Exportation of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts or Goods, procured in return of them, that the Gold and Silver, which with much Induſtry, and length of time, had been gotten by Foreign Traffick, ſhould be retained and preſerved, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting for that purpoſe the Exportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, and diſcouraging the Importati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Conſumption of unneceſſary Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Commodities, that they might Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in Goods to a greater value than they Imported, that all Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to Export Coin might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, it appearing by ſome extracts of our Trade for ſome years. In the Reign
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34354:31"/>of <hi>Edward</hi> III, and down to the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> II, that our Exports uſually exceeded our Imports by one Third in Value, and the Gold and Silver we had lately in the Nation, Coin'd, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coin'd, gotten from Foreigners in thoſe Reigns, amounts to a demonſtration, that our Treaſure encreaſed while ſuch Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods were obſerv'd, and that our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers were ſo far in the right, as to the management of Trade, for the gaining of Treaſure from Foreigners.</p>
               <p>And tho' ſince the enlarging of our Trade, by Improving our own Products and Manufactures, and Exporting more of them, we have reaped more Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies and Advantages by Trade than when it was narrow and confined, for which Reaſon, all endeavours ought to be employ'd ſtill to promote it, yet ſeeing the ſecurity and continuance of all our Trades doth in ſo great meaſure depend upon the Retaining of our Coin, and it is certain, that as our Gold and Silver was gotten by Foreign Trade, ſo it may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be conſumed by it. We ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to uſe all means and joyn all our endeavours, that we may not only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve or increaſe theſe Conveniences and Advantages, but may improve and add to our Treaſure alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:34354:32"/>Since the year 1666 we have devia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from thoſe ancient Rules and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods formerly obſerved, and purſued o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers quite contrary, for inſtead of ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out our Goods to purchaſe Coin, we have been more careful and Induſtrious to encourage Trades which have carried out our Coin or Bulion to purchaſe Goods, and by promoting the Conſumption of Foreign Commodities at home, have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the Balance, and occaſioned the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of Goods to a much geater va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue than we have Exported, by which we have not only conſumed a great part of the Treaſure we had, but all the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion that hath been brought in by our good Trades ſince that year.</p>
               <p>This <hi>anno</hi> 1666, is fixt for the year of our declenſion, becauſe the Exportation of our Gold and Silver did manifeſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe ſoon after that year, and was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by the many materials we bought in Foreign parts for the Rebuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>London</hi> and Goods for the finiſhing and furniſhing of the New Built houſes, as likewiſe by the encreaſe of Luxury, and the expenſive way of living, that followed thereupon, and the enlarging of ſome Trades ſoon after that year, which were carried on by the Exportation of our
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:34354:32"/>Coin or Bullion. For the means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to know whether we have encreaſed or decreaſed our Treaſure or Riches ſince that year, by our Foreign Traffick, muſt be by examining and making a Judgment on the Species and ſorts of Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which have been the Subject of Trade, and thereby to underſtand, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it has conſiſted of ſuch Traffick, that the Products and Returns may be ſaid to be the moſt uſeful Treaſure of a Nation, the increaſing of which is particularly meant by acquiring Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es by a Foreign Trade.</p>
               <p>It is not expected that what may be ſaid upon this Subject ſhould receive a general approbation. Some will be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to examine paſt miſcarriages in the management of Trade, others may be careleſs to fix their thoughts upon remote and diſtant dangers: And indeed ſuch thoughts as lead us to a diſcovery, that we are now growing poor, and in a decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtate, cannot be ſo pleaſing and acceptable, as what would perſwade us, that we are becoming rich: whatſoever ſooths Men up and indulges them in their preſent, (if pleaſing enjoyments, tho truly never ſo deſtructive,) uſually
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34354:33"/>finds better acceſs, and more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able reception, than perſuaſion, to ſelf denial and amendment: and whereas profit is the great Engine that moves in all matters relating to Trade, particular intereſts will always accompany, and conſequently interpoſe in all inquiries re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to it, and where that prevails, no arguments have power enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince and ſubdue. None but ſuch perſons, as will conſider Trade with an inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, as well as impartial deſire, to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the truth, can poſſibly make a true Judgment of it.</p>
               <p>In all caſes, where demonſtration can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be had, ſuch methods ought to be taken, ſuch Proof and Arguments admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as the matter under examination is capable to afford, the clearing the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Aſſertion will much depend upon a determination, by what ways and means, this Nation may get Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from foreigners by Trade; and if we have of late years taken ſuch Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, or Ways: and upon a calculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Coin we formerly had, and now have.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:34354:33"/>Tho the Ways and Means that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons have to get Riches for their own uſe, and to conſume the Treaſure of the Nation, may be many, yet the ways that we can put in practice to make an addition to the Treaſure of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by getting it from foreign Nations by Trade, may be comprehended under a few Heads, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By exporting to, and ſelling in foreign Countries, Goods which may yield more there, than the Goods we buy may coſt. By the imployment of our Ships in the Service of foreigners; and by our Factors or Merchants, reſiding or trading with foreigners, ſuch overplus on the Sales and Riches ſo gotten, being brought home in Gold or Silver, or what elſe by the being Durable and Valuable, may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be eſteemed the Treaſure of the Nation.</p>
               <p>And as it is not obvious there are any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ways and means by which we can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly get much from foreigners by Trade, ſo upon a further examination we may be convinced, that the contrary practices will have a quite contrary effect, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion a diminution of our Publick Store, by giving foreigners opportunities to drein us of what we have.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:34354:34"/>To examine whether we have taken ſuch methods as could enable us to get Treaſure from Foreigners by Trade, ſince the year 1666, Some uſe muſt be made of Calculations, grounded upon our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports and Imports, which tho they may be uncertain, as to particular Trades, becauſe we do not only Export our own Products, but many Goods from our Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and from other Countries; and that ſometimes Goods purchaſed abroad, with the produce of ſuch, are not all brought home, but ſent to ſome other Country, and conſumed there, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it may be difficult to adjuſt, how many of the Goods brought home are conſumed here, or re-exported, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Goods Exported, are ſent to the ſame place for which they are Entered: or what part of particular Trade is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by Exchange; yet no ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions of Goods, or Countries, Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, or mixtures can have any reſpect or make any ſuch difficulty in calculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon our Exports and Imports in groſs, or upon all our Trade, if ſuch could be had truly ſtated, becauſe where all is included, ſuch Objections cannot have any Weight.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:34354:34"/>By ſuch Extracts and Calculations as have been offered to publick view, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the year 1668 our Importati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Goods far exceeded our Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the year 1675 yet more, and that the year 1688, being the year before the War, we Imported the value of Six Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, but did not Export the value of Four Millions, and it alſo appears that we have Annually Exported ſince the year 1666, great quantities of Bullion.</p>
               <p>It is agreed that theſe Extracts are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Objections, for want of ſuch At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, as are neceſſary to render them Authentick; but till others can be had that may carry more Authority; it not being apparent that any particular intereſt could induce any perſon to take ſuch pains to deceive others, and on the contrary, it being notorious, that the Importation and Conſumption of foreign Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the Exportation of Bullion, hath much encreaſed upon us ſince that year; We may upon good reaſon believe that we did Import to a greater value than we Exported, whether much or little, is not material, as it relates to this particular examination, whether we could by ſuch trading get any Treaſure from fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:34354:35"/>As for the Arguments that have been frequently offered to make out that it was for our advantage to permit the Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our Bullion, or Coin, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe Goods in foreign Parts, becauſe we re-exported of the Goods brought home, ſuch quantities as brought us in more Bullion from other Countries than we ſent out, or that by ſpending ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities at home, we have prevented the going out of more Bullion, to ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Country, to purchaſe the like ſorts of Goods at dearer rates, or that by ſpending ſuch Goods at home, we have ſaved our own, and augmented our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portations. Such Arguments (if the fact were true) can only be of weight to take off the blame from one Trade to lay it on ſome other, but not to excuſe our Trade in general from having decreaſed our Treaſure.</p>
               <p>For if upon an Eſtimate of our Exports and Imports in groſs, it be true, that we have all the years aforementioned, taken from foreigners, year by year, or upon the ſum total of all the ſaid years; Goods to greater value, computed upon their coſt abroad, than all the Goods we have Exported and Sold to them have produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, then notwithſtanding the addition
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:34354:35"/>of the <hi>India</hi> or other Goods to our own Products exported, and all the pretended advantages by the Conſumption of ſuch Goods at home, it will appear, that we have been under an impoſſibility of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Treaſure from foreign Nations, ſince the year 1666.</p>
               <p>As for the greateſt part of Trade, which is carryed on by exchanging of Goods for Goods, it doth not appear that the Goods brought in, (however con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for our uſe) do more deſerve to be eſteemed the Treaſure of the Nation, than the Lead, Tin, or what other goods we ſent out, if ſuch had been kept here, and as for the overplus which we have taken over and above what our goods produced, we ſent out, unleſs we can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the foreigners did give them to us, we muſt conclude, that our Gold and Silver was carried off to pay for them: and that we have thereby conſumed our Treaſure, unleſs we will ſuppoſe that ſuch goods brought in, tho of no ſolid uſe, or long ſince conſumed, or periſhed, do how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever as well deſerve to be eſteemed the Treaſure of the Nation, as Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. And as it is impoſſible we ſhould get Treaſure from foreigners, by the bulk of Trade, whilſt our Imports exceed our
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34354:36"/>Exports. So upon an examination of ſome particular Trades it will appear that we have conſumed our Treaſure.</p>
               <p>The Trades that have had the greateſt over Balance, and is well known have moſt occaſioned the Exportation of Coin or Bullion, are thoſe to <hi>Denmark, Swede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France and India:</hi> Aſſertions that we have re-exported ſo many of the goods purchaſed with our Coin exported, as have brought us in more Bullion than we ſent out, if the ſaid Trades be taken joyntly as they refer to the Nation, will not appear to be well grounded if it be conſidered, that the goods brought in from <hi>Denmark, Swedeland</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> are for our own Conſumption, and that very few of them were ever re-exported, and that the general expence of thoſe from <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> at home, has prevented the Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of great quantities of thoſe brought thence alſo, and tho many are re-expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet few to ſuch Countries or Places, as can afford us Bullion in return; if not, and the returns be in goods, ſuch can no more make us amends for the Bullion exported, than goods purchaſed with our Bullion ſent direct to <hi>France, Swedeland</hi> or <hi>Denmark,</hi> for notwithſtanding the circulation to <hi>India,</hi> ſuch Trade termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34354:36"/>in exchanging our Gold and Silver for goods, and muſt have the ſame effect as to the conſumption of our Gold and Silver (according to the quantity of Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion ſent out) as any of our European Trades that are carried on by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of it: for tho by the advance we make upon the goods we bring from <hi>India,</hi> we may have more European goods for our Money, than if we had ſent our Bullion direct to ſuch European Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, to buy them. Yet being the Bullion which was ſent out of the Nation to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe ſuch goods remains in <hi>India,</hi> it is as much a diminution of our Treaſure, as what is ſent out direct to any Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pean Country, unleſs in ſuch caſes where ſuch goods by a re-exportation bring us in our Bullion again.</p>
               <p>As we have not got Treaſure from Foreigners by our Trade in goods of late years, becauſe we have imported to a greater value than we have exported. So not by letting out our Ships to Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, for ſince the year 1666 we have not reaped the advantages we did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly by the imployments which our Ships had in the Service of the <hi>Venetians, Portuguezes, Genoueſes,</hi> and other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. What has been gotten by Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:34354:37"/>or Factors, trading in foreign Countries, or from foreign Places, and has been brought home in Bullion or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther durable goods, cannot be diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed nor compacted: But as it has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been conſiderable, ſo ſuch induſtry deſerves all Encouragement and Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>As it may thus appear, that we have not been in a way of getting ſince the year 1666. So upon an examination of the State of our Coin it will appear, that we have conſumed a great part of the Treaſure we had in the year 1666, and alſo, what has ſince been brought in by our Foreign Trades.</p>
               <p>Tho the accounts of what Money was coined in former Reigns be perplext with a mixture of what was re-coin'd in thoſe Times by Authority, and the accounts of later years, ſince the Act paſt for the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging of Coinage, <hi>An.</hi> 1666, by what was Coin'd from our hammer'd Money mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted down for the advantage of the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weight and from Clippings; and therefore it cannot be computed by ſuch accounts, what Coin we had in the Nation, <hi>An.</hi> 1666, or what we have now, yet in this preſent conjuncture, a probable judgment may be made of our Silver Coin, from Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:34354:37"/>upon the late re-coinage, for notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that ſome of the old hammered clipt Money brought in to be re-coined was taken by weight, and not by tale; yet it is computed upon good grounds, that the hammer'd clipt Money brought in amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ten Millions, which is demonſtration that there was ten Millions of that Coin in the Nation before the year 1666, becauſe no hammered Money was Coined by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority after 1663, and the falſe Coins brought in were inconſiderable.</p>
               <p>Soon after the year 1666, when the Bullion brought in by our good Trade, was not ſufficient to anſwer the demands for Exportation, and the Act for incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging coinage was paſt, picking and culling for the melting Trade increaſed, and by ſome informations made with ſuch as did uſually cull and weigh, it appears that they found the old hammered Money the weightieſt near one third for their purpoſe. For many of the old ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mered half Crowns, had an over-weight of three pence or more, occaſion'd by the method practiſed in the coining of that ſort of Money from Barrs. Upon which it may be preſumed that between the years 1666 and 1696, at leaſt three Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of that Coin was melted down,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34354:38"/>which was alſo in the Nation before the year 1666, to which muſt be added, what was coined out of the Breeches Coin, and out of the Bullion brought in by Trade, and coined into mill'd Money before the year 1666, which is computed at one Million. Which three ſums amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Fourteen Millions, it may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed was in the Nation of good Silver Money in the year 1666, and it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Accounts of our late Coinage (tho much of our Plate has been melted down and Coined alſo) that we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced all to Seven Millions of unclipt Money, which being but half ſo much as we had, we may conclude that we have conſumed Seven Millions of our Silver Coin, ſince the year 1666.</p>
               <p>And as it is probable, we have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed ſo much of the Coin we had; So alſo, all the Silver Bullion that has been brought in by our Trade ſince that year, which may be computed at 500000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> and to the year 1688 (that the late War begun) is 22 year, and added to the Seven Millions conſumed of what we had, makes Eighteen Millions.</p>
               <p>Tho it be true that theſe Eleven Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was brought in by Trade, yet if it appear that ſince the year 1666 we have conſumed of the Coin we had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny great
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34354:38"/>quantity: and alſo, the whole of what has been brought in ſince by all our Trades, it will corroborate the judgment that has been made upon our Exports and Imports, and that we have decreaſed our Treaſure by Trade, ſince the year 1666.</p>
               <p>The Advocates for a free Exportation of Bullion to <hi>India,</hi> uſually affirm, that by that Trade more Bullion has been brought in, than carried out, (tho it is well known thoſe Exportations have been very great) and they have depended on arguments grounded thereupon, to have that Trade encouraged. Others are as violent in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the <hi>French</hi> Trade, affirming by that Trade more Bullion has alſo been brought in than carried out; tho it be difficult to decide, what has been brought in by the one, or carried out by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet being it cannot be doubted, but that we have Annually brought in great ſums of Bullion, by the Trades carried on by the Exportation of our Goods and Products, at leaſt 500000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> it ſhould be granted, that we have conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our bad Trades, what we have got by our good. Unleſs thoſe that are of a contrary opinion can make out where ſuch Bullion brought in by our good Trades, is to be found in the Nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:34354:39"/>As our Gold Money, has not been late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly re-coined, ſo no good Judgment can be made, whether we have now more or leſs than we had before 1666. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the charge of coinage is paid by the Publick, it cannot be doubted, but that many of our Guineas have been Coined over and over, it being impoſſible to Coin them ſo exact, that they may not carry ſome ſmall over-weight, which has proved a ſufficient temptation to have them melted down and re-coyned, and probably has been the chief occaſion of the coining ſo great a number, as appear by the Accounts of the Mint to have been coined ſince their Original, <hi>anno</hi> 1663. it not being probable that the Trade for <hi>Africa,</hi> nor others, or the old Gold that was melted down have afforded Gold for ſo great a Coinage; but if it be concluded that we have now more Guineas than we had in 1666, yet being our Gold Coin has not been found ſo uſeful to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, as that of Silver, Guineas ſeldom appearing in any great quantities for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in the carrying on of Trade, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs when they paſs current beyond their due proportion, and in caſe of an exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency, not to be depended on to help the Government, becauſe in ſuch caſes are
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34354:39"/>moſt likely to be hoarded, therefore no little increaſe of Gold Coin can make amends for the great quantity of our Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Coin conſumed, nor any ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Plate or Jewels.</p>
               <p>The improvement of our Lands, and encreaſe of People, Quick-ſtocks, Houſes and Ships, ought not to be allowed as Articles of Riches or Treaſure gotten from Foreigners, for tho Foreign Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick has given great encouragement to the encreaſe of ſuch Riches and Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, yet they deſerve no more to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed Treaſure gotten from Foreigners, than our Handicrafts Wares or Goods made by our own people, with our own materials. As Trade has encreaſed, ſo building of Ships, which, and the Houſes built, and improvements made of Lands are made valuable, and brought to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by an induſtrious improvement of our own, by the labour of our people: The materials which we have taken from Foreigners for ſuch buildings, tho they have coſt us dear, becauſe they have of late been moſt purchaſed with our Coin, yet they cannot be eſteemed to be of much value, after they are converted to ſuch uſes, therefore ought not to be reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned as a ſtock of Riches, or Treaſure
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34354:40"/>remaining in the Nation, gotten from Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, but as uſeful and neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies or riches gotten by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of our own, by the labour of our People. The Foreign Materials be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inconſiderable compared with the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue we put upon our Lands, Houſes and Ships.</p>
               <p>The encreaſe of the Cuſtoms, may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford a good argument, that Trade has encreaſed, but not that we have therefore gotten Treaſure from Foreigners by it, and the addition has been much occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by additional Duties, and new Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſts, which if they were diſtinguiſht or ſeparated from the old Cuſtoms; and it ſhould appear that the old Cuſtoms have encreaſed, yet it cannot be proof, that we have got Treaſure by Trade, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Cuſtoms being higheſt on Goods Imported, and low on Goods Exported, the encreaſe of the Cuſtoms has been oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by large Importations, which as before mentioned, have been ſo far from encreaſing our Treaſure, that ſuch have been the chief cauſe of decreaſing it, becauſe they have exceeded our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:34354:40"/>Coſtly Furniture of Houſes, Sumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Apparel and Equipage, may be good Arguments to prove that we once had plenty of Treaſure, but as with private Families, the more they ſpend in ſuch things, the leſs they lay up and retain, in what is more valuable; ſo with Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, eſpecially when ſuch expences are generally attended with a high courſe of living, and ſupported by the Importa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Foreign Commodities, purchaſed with our Coin or Bullion; and being the Conſumption of theſe Foreign Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by all Ranks and Degrees have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned that our Importations have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded our Exports. Inſtead of afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any argments that we are Rich, they demonſtrate that we have gone on con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming the Riches we had.</p>
               <p>That we have a Stock of Iron, Lead, Tin, and of our own Manufactures, is owing to our induſtry, and is a proof that we are not all given up to idleneſs, nor to the promoting of Foreign Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures, but not, that we have got Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from Foreigners by Foreign Trade, and it may be a queſtion if we had <hi>an.</hi> 1688, a greater Stock of Goods of foreign growth, than we had 1666, and which of them, or to what value deſerve to be
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:34354:41"/>eſteemed the Treaſure of the Nation. And if they could be diſtinguiſhed and eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they would probably appear ſo inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, compared with the Bullion and Coin we have conſumed, as that they would not deſerve the title of an Article in computations of our Riches.</p>
               <p>That this Nation has lately man'd out great Fleets, and maintained great Armies, are good marks and ſigns, that we had Ships and People, and that we had not conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all our Treaſure, before the War, but ſuch marks and ſigns of Strength and Power ought not to be taken as a proof that we had not conſumed part of our Treaſure, before the War, by Foreign Traffick: Or that we might not have managed the War with more advantage, and have been leſs in Debt, if we had been ſtored with more Coin to have circulated for the payment of the charge. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we conſumed more Bullion by the War, than was in thoſe years brought in by Trade; or whether we ſhould have conſumed by thoſe Trades which have uſually carried out Coin, and were inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by the War, more Bullion, if they had not been interrupted, than was conſumed by the War, may ſooner be diſputed than decided; therefore if it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:34354:41"/>that we did conſume our Coin or Bullion by Trade, before the late War, and there be a danger, that without ſome alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in the courſe of Trade, we ſhall not repleniſh our Stores, but go on con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming, not only the Stock we have, but all the Bullion that can be expected to come in by our good Trades hereafter, inſtead of diſputing how it is gone, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations how to prevent a further Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and to recover what we have loſt, will be moſt uſeful.</p>
               <p>After a little more banding of Maxims and Notions refering to Trade, and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations of the Conſequences that have or may attend our ſending out Coin or Bullion to purchaſe Goods, it is proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that we may at laſt come to agree in this Fundamental Poſition.</p>
               <p>That of the Stock or Capital of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, our Product and Manufactures, or Goods procured by them, are the only part or proportion that ſhould be allowed to be ſent out for the purchaſing of Goods from abroad, and for the carrying on of Foreign Trade, for as long as our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portations were confined to ſuch, we were ſecure againſt having our Treaſure conſumed by Trade, and had it in our power to make additions, by good hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34354:42"/>in the conſumption of Foreign Commodities. But as all Exportations of Coin or Bullion for trade, muſt be, either to buy Goods in Foreign Parts, or for the payment of Debts contracted for Goods taken, ſo it was a project in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture dangerous, becauſe it put us upon parting with what was moſt valuable and durable, to be exchang'd for Goods pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhable and not ſo uſeful, and the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that could be invented to make us act the part of Prodigals, and conſume our Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by ſpending more than our income.</p>
               <p>Being one of the Ends deſigned by trade is the gaining of Gold and Silver, and the Landed-men or others, not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately concerned in Foreign Traffick, (who make the greateſt part of the whole Body) cannot reap any manner of advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by the immediate Exportation of what we now have, nor by the Importation of any hereafter, unleſs it be retained and preſerved in the Nation. The keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it here being that only which makes it uſeful, for the promoting of our Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Trades, and of all Profeſſions and Imployments, or for advancing or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of Lands, Payments of Rents, as well as for a Stock of Wealth and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure always ready to be imployed for
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:34354:42"/>defence of the Nation: So theſe advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages may juſtly be expected as a reward, by thoſe who by their Products or La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour have furniſhed Materials, for the procuring of it.</p>
               <p>As they muſt be deprived of all ſuch advantages by ſuch Exportations, and the ſafety of the Publick Peace, upon which all depends, endangered thereby: So it appears too much to be adventured, upon a bare affirmation or ſuppoſition that we Import, by thoſe Trades that carry out Bullion, more than we Export, and that the giving up of ſuch Benefits and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for the particular advantage of ſome few that may enrich themſelves by the Exportation of it, will be prejudicial to the Landed-men, and all others not concerned immediately in Trade, if a want of Coin ſhould enſue.</p>
               <p>As there is a conſtant conſumption of Gold and Silver at home, by wearing and loſing, for gilding, of Fringes, Laces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as well as by Exportation, for the purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of ſome Commodities which we ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely want, and cannot other ways be had, and by private ways that cannot be prevented: So in caſe of a War, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of it; a Famine, or other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental neceſſities, much larger ſums will
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:34354:43"/>be Exported, for which as we ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to be provided, ſo it is probable we ſhall have occaſion to exhauſt ſo much of what may be brought in, from time to time hereafter, as that without any general encouragement, or permiſion to Export it, we ſhall not be in any danger of multiplying our Coin too faſt.</p>
               <p>The Coin that we muſt depend on, to circulate for the uſe of the Government, and Commerce, is the Stock of Silver Money which we may at any time have over and above what peoples particular occaſions require for the payment of Rents, ſmaller Expences, and Marketing, and tho it be true, that there has been near ſeven Millions Coined, and that there is ſome old hammered Money, or ſome of the former milled Money, now in the Nation; yet on the other hand it ought to be conſidered, how much we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to Foreigners, for what was brought in upon the Million Lottery, Annuities, Publick Stocks, and Funds, and either has been carried out again in part, ſince the re-coining of our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or may in time be carried off in Specie, and how much has been melted down of the old or new Money, that it
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:34354:43"/>might have the priviledge of Bullion, or has been Exported to purchaſe Bullion of our Neighbours, to make proviſion to buy load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>India,</hi> for above forty Ships that have been diſpatched ſince the late Peace, or are now going for thoſe Parts, and alſo how much has been exported for the Northern Trades, or <hi>French</hi> ſmugling Trade, or to be exchanged for Gold at a loſing rate, of which, tho no exact computation, can be made, yet as it may be concluded, that the extraordinary Rates given for Bullion, have afforded great Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the melting Trade, ſo that much of our old or new Coyn has been melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down and exported, notwithſtanding the late Act, and that much of our Coin has been alſo exported ſince the late re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coinage, and that we have not Seven Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of Silver Coin now in the Nation, computing Old and New.</p>
               <p>If we have but three Millions of People, which may be preſumed to have always ſome ſmall ſtock of Money for the buying of conveniencies for their uſe, and one Million of Houſe-keepers that are under ſome obligations to have ſome Stock by them, to buy Proviſions and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for their Families, and that what is ſo imployed, or in the Payments of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:34354:44"/>Rents, muſt always circulate for thoſe uſes, impoſſible to be drawn off for the uſe of the Government, or Trade, (no not in caſe of an Exigency) and that ſuch occaſions may take up at leaſt four Millions of the Silver Coin we have (Sir <hi>William Petty</hi> having computed much more to be neceſſary for thoſe uſes) then it will deſerve a ſerious conſideration whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three Millions of Silver Money be ſufficient for the Government and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and in what time it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, if great Encouragement be given to Exportation by a Prodigal conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Foreign Commodities at home, the increaſe and decreaſe of our Coin and Bullion, intirely depending on the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of Trade.</p>
               <p>From the price of Bullion we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude our Coin muſt decreaſe, unleſs ſome alterations be made in the courſe of Trade, that we may bring in more Bullion, or ſend out leſs; 4 <hi>d.</hi> to 6 <hi>d. per ounce</hi> which ſome Silver in Bullion is now worth more, than when Coined, muſt prevent (as long as that, or any little advantage is to be had) the bringing into the Mint to be Coin'd, any of the Bullion that may be Imported, and occaſion the melting down the Silver we have, whether Coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:34354:44"/>or in Plate, to be Exported, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent price of Bullion being of it ſelf a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient demonſtration that we now car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry out more than we bring in, which cannot be prevented by any Law, unleſs the cauſe be removed,</p>
               <p>That the price of Bullion now is much higher than it was before the re-coining of our Silver, has been occaſioned by the now want of the Clippings and weighty Money that we had then, what was than given for Silver in Bullion more then it was worth when Coined, was only what thoſe Traders could get as a reward to themſelves for carrying on that unlawful Trade, as long as that ſtock continued, there was not only Bullion to make up what was brought from abroad, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to anſwer all demands for Exportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but to furniſh the Mint for Coinage alſo, as it did appear by the great quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that were carried in, not of Foreign Coin ſince the year 1675, and the Gold brought in return of Silver ſent out ſome years before our re-coinage, and therefore what was Coined in thoſe years, was not a real increaſe of our Coin, but a melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of the Clippings of the old, and making it new Money for private lucre, and we may conclude that the melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34354:45"/>down of our Coin will not be totally extinguiſht, as long as the Act for the incouraging of Coinage continues in force, for as neither Gold nor Silver can be ſo exactly Coined, but there will be ſome over-weight in ſome pieces, and thoſe that carry Bullion into the Mint, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled to have out as much Coined as they carried in uncoined, any over-weight will afford a ſufficient temptation to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate, at leaſt in ſome degree, that Trade.</p>
               <p>As a ſlight information that a Mans houſe was in danger to be deſtroyed by Fire, would make the owner examine or cauſe a ſpeedy enquiry whether it were true or not, ſo this matter is of ſo great importance, that whatever objections may otherwiſe be made to the uncertainty of theſe calculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet they ſhould not hinder the making a quick as well as juſt inſpection into the preſent ſtate of our Coin, for altho, as long as our Paper Credit keeps its repute, the want of Coin may not be ſo ſenſibly felt, yet whereas ſcarcity of Coin may in Time deſtroy that, and ſeveral ways endanger the common ſafety, as it ought and cannot but be foreſeen, ſo it muſt well deſerve a timely prevention.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:34354:45"/>And ſince nothing can better conduce and be more ſerviceable to that neceſſary end, and more effectually diſpoſe us to the taking all due care to prevent the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of our publick Treaſure of Gold and Silver, than the acquiring and ſetling in our Thoughts, true and adequate Notions, in relation to our Trade, in order to a more prudent Conduct and Management of it, tho it may fall out, that particular men may vary in their opinions, and differ in the means and way to the ſame end: Yet good uſe may be made of ſuch vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of opinions, by thoſe men whoſe bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs it is to judge of both, and whoſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity may better qualifie them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Truth.</p>
               <p>The Author of the Book entitled <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes on the Publick Revenues and Trade, Part</hi> II. in oppoſition to what is here laid down, <hi>viz.</hi> That we have decreaſed our Riches by Trade, ſince the year 1666, after ſeveral Aſſertions tending to diminiſh the eſteem and value of Gold and Silver, and uſe of Coin; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing endeavoured to repreſent how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous it may be, to abound therewith, has given long Catalogues of riches, and of marks and ſigns of being rich, which he begins Page the <hi>17th</hi> in his uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:34354:46"/>imperill Style. <hi>WE ſhall therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to define what may properly be termed the Riches of the Nation:</hi> And before he has concluded his Catalogue, he gives himſelf an anſwer, to moſt of his Marks and Signs, page 20. <hi>But a Country may have all the outward marks of Wealth, which have been deſcribed, and yet its condition be bad and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound at bottom.</hi> And as for Buildings, Edifices, Improvements of Lands, new Foundations, increaſe of Quick-ſtock, and many other particulars he mentions in his Catalogue of Riches, as ſuch have not been brought from Foreign Countries, ſo it cannot be preſumed, that they have been gotten by Foreign Trade, and if not, then ſuch have no relation to the matter, upon which he grounds his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, for thoſe accidental expreſſions in the Tract he mentions, <hi>as to our having decreaſed our riches ſince the year</hi> 1666 <hi>by Trade,</hi> could not have any reference to riches gotten by our Products and Labour at home, the whole Tract being in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Authors affirmation of gains made by Foreign Trade.</p>
               <p>And as the Author in his Arguments to confute that Aſſertion, has not kept to the matter in queſtion, but has intermixt in his Catalogue of Riches, all manner of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:34354:46"/>things we have, that are deemed riches, as if all were acquired by Foreign Trade: So he has ſpent many pages in Skirmiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Poſitions of his own invention, for as the Author doth not quote any pages; ſo it doth not appear there were any paſſages in the Tracts he mentions, that repreſent the Nation to be poor, as he infers: But on the contrary, in that Tract, intituled, <hi>A Diſcourſe of Trade and Coin,</hi> p. 152. it is Printed, <hi>It appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the coining of our Money, the Trade we yet drive, and great Fleets we have, that there is not only an ability in the Nation, but alſo a Spirit in the People, which if cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated, improved and encouraged by proper methods, might be ſufficient to attain the End, (propoſed) nothing can be more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, than that good reſolutions, upon ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid conſultations ſhould be taken, in order thereto,</hi> which with many other ſuch like expreſſions in thoſe Tracts, as they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be underſtood to repreſent the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be ſo poor as this Author ſuggeſts; So the ſcope and deſign of thoſe Tracts was to excite us to Induſtry, and good Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry in the Conſumption of Foreign Commodities, that we might keep and increaſe our Coin, in order to grow rich, therefore all the Authors repeated reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34354:47"/>upon that ſcore, have no Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but his own fancy.</p>
               <p>Neither do his Arguments <hi>p.</hi> 44. from the great Expences the Nation has been at to ſupport the late War, make for his purpoſe; it being well known, that moſt of the Money collected to carry on the War, was raiſed by a Land, and Pole Taxes, Exciſe on Beer and Ale, Duties on Malt, Salt, Leather, Stamp-paper, Glaſs-windows, Births and Marriages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which have no particular relation to Foreign Trade, becauſe ſuch Taxes were paid by the Landed-men, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumers, the Traders only concerned in proportion with others. What was raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Cuſtoms and Duties upon Foreign Goods imported, is uſually alſo paid by the Conſumer at laſt, which Taxes, Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Importations, all have been ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to pay by their Profits and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages ariſing to each reſpectively, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their profeſſions, or intereſt in Land, Trade, or by any Labour or Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whatſoever. The circulation of our Coin occaſioned by ſuch Profeſſions, and by the labour beſtowed in improving our Annual Crops, affording a conſtant ſupply or nouriſhment to all ſuch Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Profeſſions, by promoting, buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:34354:47"/>Selling, labour, foreign Trade, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſeveral ſorts of buſineſs did ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the People to pay the Taxes collected for the Charge of the War.</p>
               <p>As the Author agrees in his account of of Coinage, from <hi>p.</hi> 29, to 40, that we had in the Nation, <hi>an.</hi> 1688, at leaſt Nine Millions of old hammer'd Money, and ſays, that one Million more had been lately melted down. So he will find that there was above one million melted and coined into Mill'd Money, between 1660 and 1666; and as he agrees there was much old hammered Money melted down. So up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a further inquiry he may be ſatisfied, that it could not amount to leſs than Three Millions, and as he ſeems to be of opinion <hi>p.</hi> 39, that we have not now in the Nation as much Money as ever: So he muſt agree that all that has been brought in by Trade ſince that year has been carried out again, becauſe there is no appearance that we have now any of it in the Nation, and then he will not find ſo much cauſe to wonder as he doth, <hi>p.</hi> 40. <hi>What ſhould be the meaning of thoſe that are of opinion, that the Exportation of Bullion is ſo deſtructive to the Nation.</hi> That <hi>Xenophon</hi> ſhould ſo long ago agree with the Author's opinion, That the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:34354:48"/>of Coin or Bullion, in the way of Traffick, could not be prejudicial to a Country, <hi>p.</hi> 360, 361, is rather a great Credit to the old Proverb, <hi>that good Wits Jump,</hi> than to the Authors aſſertion that it is convenient for <hi>England</hi> to Export Bullion, becauſe it was good for <hi>Athens.</hi> The different circumſtances of Countries make that convenient for one Country which may not be ſo for another; it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by <hi>Xenophon</hi>'s diſcourſe, upon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving the Revenue of that State, that <hi>Athens</hi> had Silver Mines, and that much of that Country was too barren to receive the common improvement of Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry; as it is quite contrary with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſo we ought to be acted by different reaſons. <hi>Xenophon</hi> concludes that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with his opinion, <hi>That the</hi> Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians <hi>ſhould conſult the Oracle once more, that they might know to the protection of what Gods they might recommend the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of that enterprize:</hi> As the Author would not have <hi>Xenophon</hi>'s opinion fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in that particular, though proper for the <hi>Athenians,</hi> ſo not his opinion as to the Exportation of Silver, becauſe it was <hi>Xenophon</hi>'s, unleſs it appeared that it is convenient now for <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:34354:48"/>And the like reaſons may be given to make out, that tho it may be convenient for <hi>Holland, Venice, Genoua</hi> and <hi>Leivorne,</hi> yet not for <hi>England.</hi> The Author alſo adds, to ſupport his own, and <hi>Xenophon</hi>'s opinion, <hi>That the Nations that have a way of bringing in Bullion to anſwer what is carried out, are in this ſenſe upon the ſame foot, with Countries, that have Mines in their poſſeſſions, and that Bullion becomes there a Commodity like any other of its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Argument is grounded on a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that it is eaſie for us to get Gold and Silver enough from Foreigners by Trade, not only to ſerve our own occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions at home, but to Export alſo, which upon peruſual of what has been already ſaid, and will follow in the concluſion of this Diſcourſe, it is preſumed will not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be true in Fact; and what he adds from obſervations on the Spaniſh Monarchy is grounded on a ſort of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning that contradicts it ſelf. <hi>P.</hi> 362. <hi>That the Gold and Silver brought from</hi> Spain <hi>by ſtealth are the very Tools, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wiſer Nations have wrought;</hi> as it is true, why may it not be feared, if we permit too much to be carried out, that we may in time want ſuch Tools alſo, and find them
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:34354:49"/>in the hands of other Nations, that may uſe them to our prejudice; or rather, is it not plain, that what has been carried from us, has been already uſed in foreign parts, to imploy their people in work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Manufactures, to the hindrance of ours. The <hi>Sweedes</hi> did not ſet up their Fabricks till they had got, not only our Wooll, (by the way of <hi>Scotland</hi>) but our Coin from hence alſo; and the <hi>French</hi> have much increaſed theirs, by the ſame me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod: Not to mention what has been done with it in <hi>India,</hi> which has been often diſcourſed: <hi>That the Prohibitions in</hi> Spain <hi>to Export thoſe Species, were a bar to their induſtry, and rendred their Treaſure uſeleſs,</hi> is grounded on a ſuppoſition, That the words of a Law, can be effectual, tho' the Law be not at all obſerved. For he owns, and it is well known, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that Law, Gold and Silver has been conſtantly brought from thence, and therefore it is more probable that the want of coin there, and of Materials for Manufactures, and of plenty of Proviſions to make Labour Cheap, and of indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious inclinations in the People, have contributed more to the poverty of that Monarchy, than a Law that was never obſerved.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:34354:49"/>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 46. The Author ſuggeſts, that a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph, in his <hi>Eſſay on the Eaſt-India Trade, P.</hi> 16, was miſunderſtood.</p>
               <p>It is admitted, that the words of that his Paragraph, are doubtfully penned, as to what year he intended that his two Millions gain ſhould commence, or be extended, and therefore, as neceſſary in all caſes where writing is obſcure, what preceeded, and was ſubſequent to that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, relating to the ſame matter was examined, to find out the Authors mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: As it ought now again to make a judgment, whether the miſtake (if any) were occaſioned by the diſingenuity of the Author, or want of <hi>Senſe</hi> in the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; proceeding to that aſſertion, he told his Reader in that Tract</p>
               <p>P. 14. <hi>By the beſt account I can have and from impartial hands,</hi> England <hi>before the War, for ſometime, one year with another has exported for this Traffick, either in Bullion, or our Manufactures (of which our Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures may be-one eighth) about</hi> 400000 <hi>l. per an.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. 15. <hi>No one verſed in Merchandize will deny that the return from</hi> India <hi>of</hi> 200000 l. <hi>ſent out when exported to other Countries muſt increaſe the firſt cost, at leaſt four fold, and produce</hi> 800000 <hi>l.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:34354:50"/>P. 16. <hi>Nothing can be a clearer gain to this Kingdom than the return of</hi> 200000 l. <hi>conſumed at home, becauſe treble that ſum would otherwiſe be carried out for foreign Silks and Linens, which is hindred by the Importati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Commodities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. 16. <hi>I have many cogent reaſons indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing me to believe that from about</hi> Anno 1656, <hi>to</hi> 1688, <hi>this Nation hath every year gradually increaſed in riches (by what degrees is needleſs here to inſert) but upon mature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration I may ſafely ſtate that about</hi> An. 1688, <hi>the increaſe or addition to the Wealth and general Stock of</hi> England <hi>ariſing from foreign Trade, and home Manufactures was at leaſt two Millions yearly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. 17. <hi>And after much thought and ſtudy on this Subject, and by conſulting others verſed in ſpeculations of the like nature, I find that this increaſe to the Nations general ſtock did probably ariſe from the three following Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>From our Manufactures, and home Products, ſent to the Plantations, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn Exported</hi> per an.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>l.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>900000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>From our Woollen Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſent to</hi> France, Spain, Italy, Germany, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> per an.</cell>
                        <cell>500000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:34354:50"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>From the Net profit accru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Trade</hi> per an.</cell>
                        <cell>600000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>2000000</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>The Act of Navigation, which regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the Plantation Trade in favour of <hi>England,</hi> was made ſome years before 1656; and the Subſcriptions for the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, were underwrit a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 1656, which being the Trades to which he attributes moſt of his great gains, it was an inducement to believe that he did not intend that his word <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually</hi> ſhould extenuate the force of his word <hi>yearly,</hi> and confine the two Millions increaſe of Wealth to a year or two, or reduce it to an uncertainty, upon which it was computed that from 1656, to 1688 was 32 years, upon which in the Tract he mentions, he was told, that if he had ſpent ſome thought and ſtudy, where the 64 Millions were to be found, he would have done the Nation a great kindneſs.</p>
               <p>As the Author has expreſſed his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at this queſtion, in his laſt Book, <hi>p.</hi> 46, ſo in juſtice it might have been expected that he would now have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained his meaning, as to point of time
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:34354:51"/>relating to his two Millions <hi>per an.</hi> which he might eaſily have done, if he knew, as he pretends,</p>
               <p>P. 4. <hi>The general amount of our Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and to ſet down in diſtinct articles, what is our yearly amounts of both our neceſsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and luxurious Importations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſeeing the Author (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid provocation) has here again left us in the dark, it ſhall be preſumed, that it is for the ſame reaſon he gives for not publiſhing an account of the ſaid Exports, and Imports, <hi>P.</hi> 4. <hi>That it may be a diſcovery and opening of the Kingdom's ſtate and condition, that peradventure is not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſable.</hi> A politick caution, he probably forgot when he publiſht to the World the debts of the Nation, <hi>in his diſcourſe of the publick Revenues and Trade,</hi> Part the 1ſt.</p>
               <p>Happily this Author was the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned at this inquiry about the 64 Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, becauſe it carried with it a detecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his being miſtaken in his firſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to calculate Trade by his Political Arithmetick, which now he ingeniouſly confeſſes; for in this Book he rectifies ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of his former miſtaken Computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and makes others far different.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:34354:51"/>Page 376. <hi>This tract may perhaps be read by ſome whoſe curioſity may not lead them to peruſe the forementioned Diſcourſe; upon which ſcore, or to help the Reader's Memory, there ſhall again be inſerted what (upon the beſt lights we can procure) we conceive might be the general ſtate of Trade about</hi> 1688 <hi>to make up the two Millions National profits thence ariſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>per an.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>The Plantation Trade might bring in—</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>600000<hi>l.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>The</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Trade might bring in</hi> —</cell>
                        <cell>500000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>The</hi> European, African, <hi>and</hi> Levant <hi>Trades might bring in</hi> — — —</cell>
                        <cell>600000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>The Re-exports of Plantation Goods</hi> —</cell>
                        <cell>120000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>The Re-exports of</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Goods</hi> —</cell>
                        <cell>180000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>2000000</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Page 377. <hi>That upon a better view of the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Trade, than we were able to make the laſt year, when the Eſſay was written, we find the Exports to</hi> India <hi>in Bullion and Wares might be about</hi> 500000 l. per ann. <hi>of which the returns might be about</hi> 1800000 l. <hi>whereof there might be conſumed at home, to the value of</hi> 1300000 l. <hi>when it comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſecond, third, and fourth hand, as will be explained hereafter, and Re-exported to</hi> Europe <hi>at leaſt</hi> 500000 l. per ann. <hi>which</hi> 500000 l. <hi>may be ſtated as the clear gains
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:34354:52"/>by that Trade, and the ſaid</hi> 500000 l. per ann. <hi>Exported to</hi> Europe <hi>producing</hi> 680000 l. <hi>Leaves a gain of</hi> 180000 l. <hi>to the Trade of</hi> Europe.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Pag.</hi> 381. To make it plain that the ſaid 680000 <hi>l. per ann.</hi> is clear gains by that Trade.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>l.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Bought at Sales for Foreign Conſumption,</hi> per ann. —</cell>
                        <cell>— 500000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>The returns whereof may add to the</hi> European <hi>Ball,</hi> per ann. — —</cell>
                        <cell>— 180000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Saved by lowering</hi> 25 per cent. <hi>in the price of Foreign Silks.</hi> — — —</cell>
                        <cell>— 100000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>By lowering</hi> 25 per cent. <hi>in the price of Foreign Linen</hi> per ann. — —</cell>
                        <cell>— 100000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Saved in the expences of Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Goods of the like nature in the room of which,</hi> Eaſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia <hi>Goods are uſed,</hi> per ann. —</cell>
                        <cell>— 200000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Saved in the Conſumption of our home materials which theſe goods ſupply, and whereby our exportation is enlarged</hi> per ann.</cell>
                        <cell>— 100000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:34354:52"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>In all.</cell>
                        <cell>1180000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Out of which deduct for Bullion and Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Exported</hi> per ann. —</cell>
                        <cell>— 0500000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>680000</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe laſt Computations which dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from thoſe in his Eſſay on the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, it may be concluded that he publiſhed in his Eſſay what he did not underſtand himſelf, and therefore it ſhould not be thought ſtrange, that he was not well underſtood by others, in his former Computations he had reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome gains on the <hi>French</hi> Trade, which now upon better thoughts he has left out, alter'd his Computations on the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, and reduced his 900000 <hi>l.</hi> gains on the Plantation Trade, to 600000 <hi>l. per ann.</hi> and to adjuſt his two Millions <hi>per ann.</hi> gains (which he was reſolved to make up ſome way or other) he has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed his gain on the <hi>European,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>India</hi> Trade; which alterations, as they diſcover, that the Author was then mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, as he has ingeniouſly own'd, ſo
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:34354:53"/>they give ſome hopes, that upon a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſpection into Trade, he may change his opinion again.</p>
               <p>But tho' the Author would not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by others, that his two Millions yearly gain ſhould commence from 1656 yet he has by ſome expreſſions in this Book diſcover'd, that he underſtood it ſo himſelf.</p>
               <p>Page 213. <hi>We are inclined to think that the profit ariſing from the</hi> European <hi>Trade was about</hi> 600000 l. per an. <hi>added to the National Stock, which in thirty years is eighteen Millions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Page. 53. <hi>The two Millions addition of Wealth which we have mentioned became an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually converted into National Stock, was the effect of a long Peace and a Flouriſhing Trade, and was ſeen in the extenſiveneſs of our Traffick abroad, Richneſs of our Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, and houſhold Furniture, variety of new Manufactures, and in the increaſe of our Cattle, Buildings, Shipping, Plate, Jewels, Bullion, and ready Money, and in the vaſt ſtores we had by us, of our own Native Goods, and of Foreign Commodities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:34354:53"/>Here he not only ratifies the gains of two Millions <hi>per annum,</hi> but by his words long Peace and flouriſhing Trade makes it ſtronger, that it might be underſtood for many years, and gives an anſwer to the queſtion, where it was to be found, or in what it conſiſts: the examination of theſe particulars (which he notes as Riches gotten by Foreign Trade) may probably diſcover that the diſtinctions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, as the getting of Riches or Treaſure, are neceſſary to be obſerved and reſpected in all conſiderations refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Trade, and by affording ſome uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful informations, make ſome amends for the time that has been loſt, in anſwering his Reflections upon that Queſtion.</p>
               <p>It has been already aſſerted, that the gaining of Riches or Treaſure from Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners by foreign Traffick, ſignifies the bringing into the Nation ſome Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies or Commodities that by being valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and durable, and capable to be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſerviceable to the Nation or Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Politick; and of more value than was exchanged for them, can only deſerve to be eſteemed the Riches of the Nation: Extenſive traffick, which is here firſt nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe particulars, is no denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Matter, or Species; but a general name, or notion, tho many Arguments
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:34354:54"/>may be drawn from it to prove we had Trade, yet none to prove that we got two Millions <hi>per annum</hi> in thoſe years by Trade, and as it cannot be diſtinguiſh'd what part of extended Traffick is owing to our Products, Labour and natural advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or to gains made by foreign traffick; ſo it cannot be computed what proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it is part of this two Millions an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually gotten and converted into Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Stock.</p>
               <p>Richneſs of Apparel and Furniture, doth indeed conſiſt of ſeveral ſorts of goods, ſome of our own make, and ſome procured from foreign Countries, in what proportion 'tis impoſſible to be diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but as ſuch as are made of our own materials, and by our own people, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be reckoned as Riches gotten from Foreigners, or by foreign traffick, ſo ſuch as are procured from abroad in exchange of our Goods, unleſs durable and laſting, do not deſerve to be eſteemed Riches. And if a Nation be run into an extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant way of living, and purchaſe ſuch by our Bullion ſent out, then they will no more deſerve to be eſteemed as an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to the Riches of the Nation, or as true marks and ſigns, that a Nation has increaſed in riches, than that a young Spark is grown rich, or has
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:34354:54"/>added to his ſtock, becauſe he hath laid out a good part of his Patrimony, in a gaudy Suit or ſumptuous Equipape.</p>
               <p>Variety of new Manufactures if he mean of our own make (as may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, becauſe he mentions Foreign Commodities afterwards) they are moſt made of our own materials, improved by our labour, and cannot be reckoned as got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by foreign traffick, tho ſome of the materials be procured from abroad, and foreign Trade hath given a great help to the increaſe of ſuch Manufactures, and they are convenient for uſes at home, and abroad, yet it doth not follow that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, theſe Manufactures muſt be made a part of his two Millions, additional Wealth gotten by foreign Traffick.</p>
               <p>The increaſe of our quick Stock may with more reaſon be attributed to the care of our Landed-men, in permitting their Cattle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to procreate, than to foreign Trade, for tho the Victualing of Ships for foreign Trade, gives a help to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of our Proviſions, yet neither the Cattle, nor the Lands on which they feed, nor the Improvements made on them, are brought in from abroad. The increaſe is owing to the length of time, the multiplying of people, and addition
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:34354:55"/>of induſtry at home, as well as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of buildings, which are alſo the produce of our labour, helpt by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation of our Coin; for tho many Houſes, have been built by perſons who have got Eſtates by Trade, yet as ſuch Eſtates may be gotten at home, by gains made on our own people, ſo ſuch buildings ought not to be reckoned as Riches gotten from Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, and where Houſes have been built by perſons that have got their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates by foreign Traffick, ſuch buildings ought not to be reckoned as ſo gotten, but the Gold or Silver, or what elſe they brought in, that enabled them to build ſuch Houſes. And ſeeing our Ships are built with our own timber, and their value doth chiefly ariſe by that, and the labour of our people, by building, caſting the Guns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therefore they are lyable alſo to the ſame objections (ſome fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign materials excepted) and the like may be objected againſt ſtock in native growth.</p>
               <p>And as for Stock in foreign Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſometimes we have more, ſometimes leſs, as the Markets may riſe or fall, and it doth not appear that we had more in 1688 than in former years, unleſs brought in at that time upon proſpect of the War
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:34354:55"/>and if ſo, then they ought to be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as accidental, and not as a ſtanding laſting Stock. But as the beſt that can be ſaid in favour of ſuch Stocks in foreign Commodities, is that they were purchaſed in exchange of our Products: ſo unleſs it appear, that what was brought in was much more durable, valuable, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable for the Nation, than what was ſent out, ſuch Stock ought to be reckoned only as an exchange of Goods and not as an addition of Wealth to make up his Article of two Millions.</p>
               <p>Plate, Jewels, Bullion and ready Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, ſhould be agreed to be an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to the Wealth and Treaſure of the Nation, and to be a good Article to make up his two Millions <hi>per an.</hi> gotten by foreign Traffick, if the Author had made out, that we had any increaſe of thoſe Species in the years he mentions, but if it appear by what has been already offered upon that Subject, that we had decreaſed ſo much of our Coin and Bullion before the year 1688, and that our Jewels or wrought Plate (if we had then more than in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times) cannot make any ſufficient amends for it: then it muſt be agreed, that the particulars the Author has enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, are ſo far from making out where
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:34354:56"/>we could have found <hi>an.</hi> 1688, 64 Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions or 32 Millions, or what other ſum he means, by the two Millions annually gotten by Foreign Traffick, in the Trades he mentions, converted into National Stock; that nothing conſiderable can be collected from thoſe particulars, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer or make amends for the Coin and Bullion we conſumed in thoſe years, and if not, then it muſt be concluded, that we have decreaſed our Riches by Trade ſince the year 1666.</p>
               <p>But perchance this Author may be beſt convinced that his aſſertion is not well grounded (tho it be left to himſelf to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, from what years his two Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions ſhall commence) by arguments drawn from his own Computations.</p>
               <p>Page 49. <hi>By the rules of that Political Arithmetick, which is our guide in all theſe matters it doth ſeem,</hi>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>l.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>That the Stock of</hi> England <hi>was</hi> anno 1600 <hi>about</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>— 17000000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>That in thirty years it near doubled, and</hi> anno 1630 <hi>was about.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>— 28000000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:34354:56"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>That in thirty years it doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and</hi> anno 1660 <hi>was about</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>— 56000000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>That from</hi> 1680, <hi>to</hi> 1688, <hi>it above half doubled, and was</hi> 1688 <hi>about</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>— 88000000</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Scheme is calculated upon a general view, and inſpection into the Kingdoms ſtate, and every Article of it may be made out and juſtified, by as plain demonſtration as any thing of this nature is capable of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this Scheme which is confirmed by my Author, with very great aſſurance he makes the Stock of <hi>England</hi> to have increaſed 32 Millions, from <hi>an.</hi> 1660, to <hi>an.</hi> 1688, which being 28 years, is 1, 142, 857 <hi>l.</hi> 02 <hi>s.</hi> 10 <hi>d.</hi> ¼ <hi>per an.</hi> To make this up, he tells his Reader in the ſame page, that the matters comprehended in his account are coined Gold, coined Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Bullion, wrought Plate, Rings, Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, Furniture, Apparrel, ſtock for Trade, Conſumption and live ſtock in Cattle, and for fear he ſhould have forgotten to have enumerated any moveables that might be eſteemed Wealth, Stock or Riches, four (boundleſs,) <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are added and the word Conſumption is crowd
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:34354:57"/>ed in, as a matter or thing that might be accounted Wealth.</p>
               <p>It is an approved rule in common Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick, that where the ſum total is known, if the particulars differ from the ſum to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, that the account cannot be true.</p>
               <p>The ſum total of all our increaſe of Wealth, by our Products, Labour, and all foreign Trades and ways whatſoever, by our Authors account, <hi>page</hi> 49, is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted to be 32 Millions, from 1660, to 1688, that is 1,142,857.02, 10¼ <hi>per an.</hi> which makes the ſaid — 32,000000</p>
               <p>It is convenient to ſee how his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars agree with his Sum total, according to what may be gathered from them as they are ſcatter'd in his ſaid Book, <hi>page</hi> 47, which is reform'd <hi>p.</hi> 376,
<table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>On the <hi>European, Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi> and <hi>Levant</hi> Trades 600000 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> which in 28 years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to</cell>
                        <cell>16,800,000 <hi>l.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>On the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade at 500000 <hi>l. per annum</hi> in 28 years</cell>
                        <cell>14,000,000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>On the Plantation Trade 600000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> for 28 years</cell>
                        <cell>16,800,000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:34354:57"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>On the Re-exportation of Plantation goods 1200000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> in 28 years</cell>
                        <cell>03,360,000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>On the Re-exports of <hi>Eaſt India</hi> goods 180000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> in 28 years</cell>
                        <cell>05,040,000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>56,000,000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Page</hi> 413. The Author computes that we have 12 Million of fleeces of Wooll, and <hi>page</hi> 414, that our Wooll improv'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to 8 Millions <hi>per an.</hi> of which reckoning but one quarter part to be an addition of Wealth to the Nation, becauſe he ſays that only two Millions is annually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and can only be accounted as a clear gain to the Kingdom, amounts to in 28 years.</cell>
                        <cell>56,000,000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>— 112,000,000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:34354:58"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>By the increaſe of quick Stock, and the labour of our People in our Mines, and Fiſhing Trades, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it may be computed that about one Million <hi>per annum</hi> more has been added to our Stock or Riches, which in 28 years is</cell>
                        <cell>028,000,000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The ſum total 32 Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: the Particulars</cell>
                        <cell>140,000,000</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>And if the Author ſhould appeal from theſe particulars to his reſerve, as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement of time, as he will not be able to make any material objection againſt the addition of Wealth propoſed to ariſe from our products and labour and improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at home, ſo he has bound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alſo up, <hi>page</hi> 213. (as to gains) on the <hi>European, African</hi> and <hi>Levant</hi> Trades, and it is well known, that the <hi>East-India</hi> Trade has been driven at a great height ever ſince 1673, and the Plantation Trade even from the year 1650, ſo that it will be very difficult for him to draw from
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:34354:58"/>thence any very good argument to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port his computing faculty.</p>
               <p>If it be objected the gains of two Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions <hi>per ann.</hi> placed made by Foreign Trade, is to be underſtood as ariſing from our Products ſent out, and that therefore the other three Millions on our Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Goods, Product, and Labour, ought not to be reckoned alſo, then it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that we have made no addition to our Riches by the improvement of our Wooll, Products, or Labour, or elſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by Foreign Trade, whereas the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor has aſſerted, <hi>Page</hi> 376. That there was two Millions gotten annually by the Foreign Trades he mentions, and <hi>Page</hi> 414 That we export yearly two Millions in Woollen Goods, and <hi>P.</hi> 3. <hi>That of thoſe Commodities,</hi> viz. <hi>Woollen Manufactures, Tin, Lead, Leather, Fiſh, whatever we Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port yearly is a certain Wealth to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and is the foundation of all commerce:</hi> Therefore the miſtake (if any) in this Computation of One Hundred and Fourty Millions, will be beſt detected by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's giving in his next Book (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Ability he pretends to) an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Wealth we got in thoſe 28 years in diſtinct articles, how much by,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:34354:59"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>The Plantation Trades.</item>
                     <item>The <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade.</item>
                     <item>The <hi>European, African,</hi> and <hi>Levant</hi> Trades.</item>
                     <item>By our Woollen Goods.</item>
                     <item>By our Fiſhing Trades.</item>
                     <item>By our Mines, Leather, Proviſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Exported,</item>
                     <item>And by our increaſe of quick Stock, and Improvements at home.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>That he may ſee by his own accompt, ſo made up, how ill his Computations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, which will be of much more uſe, than his Anſwer to the detection made of his looſe Computations and Reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings on the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade.</p>
               <p>Page. 48. <hi>The Computations ſet down in our Eſſay have a better Foundation than our Merchant can comprehend, or have any Idea about, whoſe limited underſtanding and narrow mind, ſeems never to have had any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther object, than his own private Dealings from Port to Port.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though ſuch reflections may be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Authors Education; yet they cannot be ſo ſerviceable to make a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the matters conteſted as ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments or reaſoning upon things.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:34354:59"/>If it be objected to the aforeſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, that our Woollen Goods are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhable, and that many of them, as well as our other Products were conſumed at home, and that therefore they ought not to be Computed as an Addition of Wealth, it is anſwer'd, That only one quarter part of their value, is reckon'd as an Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to our Wealth, and the other three quarters, allowed to be conſumed, but then it is expected that the ſame argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall be admitted as to periſhable Goods brought in by Foreign Trade, and that in Computations of gain on Foreign Trade, only ſuch ſhall be eſteemed an Addition of Wealth or Treaſure to the Nation, as remain and continue durable and uſeful for the whole Body, which are the Species of Gold and Silver, as that <hi>only</hi> which converted into Coin, becomes a publick Stock for the Service of all, for ſuch other Commodities that have been brought in by Foreign Trade, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main for publick uſe, will appear to be inconſiderable in value, compared with thoſe Species, therefore if we have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed our Gold and Silver, it will juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the aſſertion, that has occaſioned much of this diſcourſe, <hi>That we have decreaſed our Riches by Trade ſince the year</hi> 1666.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:34354:60"/>As from thoſe inſtances it may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred that the Author's Computations are very uncertain, ſo upon a further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration it will appear, that to take our informations as to what is paſt, or our meaſures for the management of our Trade or for the increaſe of our Wealth for the future, from ſuch Computations will be dangerous.</p>
               <p>What he pretends to make out, <hi>Pag.</hi> 3, as to the annual income of Land, Trade, the expence of the whole People, both in War and Peace, how much the Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al's Stock increaſed in time of Peace, and impairs in time of War; and what he aſſerts <hi>P.</hi> 27. as to the general rental, <hi>P.</hi> 49. as to the Stock of <hi>England</hi> from time to time, <hi>P.</hi> 106. the State of <hi>Holland</hi> as to debts, incomes, <hi>&amp;c. P.</hi> 366. how people may be ſuſtained by the Rents of Land, Trade, and Labour, in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> and his ſeveral affirmations and accounts of Gains made by Trade.</p>
               <p>As it appears upon the firſt view that ſuch things are difficult if not impoſſible to be Computed, ſo it cannot be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that any man in his ſenſes, ſhould give Credit to ſuch Computations, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſight of vouchers or proofs which
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:34354:60"/>would conſiſt of ſo many Articles, and be ſo Voluminous, that few would think it worth their Labour to peruſe them, and then either allow ſuch Calculations to be true for much the ſame Reaſon, as ſome do ſtrange ſtories told by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers of Foreign Countries (becauſe they will not take long journeys to diſprove them) or rather not believe them at all, which will be found the ſafeſt way, and to judge of ſuch things according to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or by what we ſee or find by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</p>
               <p>Tho' it is not doubted, but that Mr. <hi>King</hi>'s Schemes, upon which the Author ſets up; have been perfected with great Labour, and deſerve to be eſteemed as great Curioſities, and that they may be of uſe in inquiries, about Rentals, Wealth, Stock, Trade, or Coin, and to make Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, where there is a neceſſity that ſome gueſs muſt be made, and that the Author has fairly quoted ſome parts of them, and that there is matter in them to be a Foundation for Writing large Volumes, and that they may ſerve as a means to bring thoſe matters they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain under debate, yet they ought not to be admitted as a Rule to make Concluſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:34354:61"/>Therefore if we ſhould follow the Authors Opinions which are moſt grounded upon theſe Schemes, becauſe he gives them the lofty Title of his <hi>Political Arithmetick,</hi> we ſhall be in as much danger to be miſlead as a man, that in a dark night follows <hi>A Will with a Wiſp.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But tho' the Schemes and Computations from which he has taken his meaſures and his aſſertions grounded on them, are liable to theſe objections, yet ſome of his advertiſements have a better Foundation, eſpecially that, Pag. 68. <hi>and the Landed Gentlemen, ſhould not be miſlead by narrow minded Perſons, who raiſe objections againſt particulars, and make concluſions in ſingle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, without having looked into the whole and conſidered how the general balance ſtands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being a very good caution, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall be added to it, but that as ſome men have narrow thoughts, ſo others have too wide, and are too apt to run up Caſtles in the Air without minding Foundations, and that tho' it be the intereſt of every Landed Man to encourage all Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at home and all Foreign Trades whatſoever, that are carried on or bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Exportation of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts and Manufactures, or Goods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured in Exchange for them. Yet to be careful how they encourage Trades that
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:34354:61"/>are carried on by the Exportation of Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion) leaſt, at laſt, they find their Pockets emptied of their Money, while a fair ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is telling them to their face. When they ſend Money to the markets to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe Goods that have been fabri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> at home, with their own Wooll, or have been procured from abroad in return of our own Product, ſuch Money ſent to <hi>London,</hi> or any other Market, for that, or any ſuch uſe, will circulate in a ſhort time, and return to the Country again, to purchaſe more Wooll, or to carry on thoſe Fabricks: But when it is ſent out of the Country to be laid out in Goods that are purchaſed abroad with our Money, That Money will be exported to purchaſe more of the ſame ſort of Goods abroad, and never return to them, and that if they depart from ſuch Rules and Maxims, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Authors two propoſitions laid down, in his <hi>Eſsay on the Eaſt India Trade, P.</hi> the 29. in order to have their Wooll ſold cheap, they may ſoon ſee the price of their Wooll and Products brought low, and the people very poor for want of Coin to imploy them, and be at as great a loſs to find out any Treaſure gotten by ſuch foreign Traffick, as the Author is
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:34354:62"/>to find out, his one hundred and fifty Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of the Bullion, that has come from the <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> in his ſaid Book, <hi>p.</hi> the 12. or the Executors and Legattees of Eſquire <hi>Wickham,</hi> what was left them by that Famous Will.</p>
               <p>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the Author, for fear this caution ſhould not be ſufficient to the Landed men, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them againſt being miſled by wrong Notions, has thought good to preſs the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter further, by Arguments grounded on Intereſt, to make this caution effectual.</p>
               <p>Page 324. <hi>When the young Nobility and Gentry employ their time and thoughts care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to inſpect and conſider the Kingdoms foreign traffick, they will evidently ſee, how much their Land-intereſt depends upon it, they will find as Trade brought land from</hi> 12 <hi>to</hi> 25, <hi>and the general rental from</hi> 6 <hi>to</hi> 14 <hi>Millions, and the Kingdoms capital from</hi> 72 <hi>to</hi> 252 <hi>Millions (reckoning Lands, Tenements, Hereditaments and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Estates</hi> 18 <hi>years purchaſe at a medium) ſo it may bring Land from</hi> 25 <hi>to</hi> 50 <hi>years purchaſe, and Lands, Tenements and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>from</hi> 18 <hi>to</hi> 36 <hi>years pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, the general rental from</hi> 14 <hi>to</hi> 28 <hi>Millions, and the Kingdoms Capital from</hi> 252 <hi>to above</hi> 1000 <hi>Millions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:34354:62"/>The Author did very wiſely to direct this paragraph and others <hi>p.</hi> 322, to the young Nobility and Gentry, for the Aſſertions are ſuch, that he had reaſon to prefume, they would not be believed by thoſe that were of age, there being ſo many viſible cauſes for the advance of Lands, and increaſe of the Kingdoms Capital, beſides the advantages we have by foreign traffick, for without detracting from the juſt merits of foreign Trade, much of the cauſe muſt be attributed to the alterations made in our Coin, which has been altered in ſeveral Reigns, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced; the Silver Money from the making of 20 <hi>s.</hi> 3 <hi>d.</hi> out of a pound troy, to be 62 <hi>s</hi> out of a pound troy, as it now ſtands; alſo to the increaſe of People, improvements by length of time, and the increaſe of Riches ariſing from our labour, and induſtry at home, for Riches ſo gotten, did of courſe occaſion an increaſe of purchaſers, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bidders in all caſes, will advance the price of any Commodity that is to be ſold.</p>
               <p>And what more particularly has been the cauſe of the advance of Lands and Rents, was the increaſe of out Coin, which is ſolely due to foreign Trade, but it was gotten when we exported in goods more than we imported, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by kept our Coin at home, inſtead of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:34354:63"/>ſending it out, but if we ſhould now be miſlead to go the contrary way, and by ſuch methods decreaſe it, in a ſhort time Lands and Rents as well as all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concerns will ſoon find the effect of it.</p>
               <p>By the Kingdoms Capital, it is not very clear, what he means in this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph. For,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 27, 28. Where he computes the Kingdoms Capital to be 252 Millions, he enumerates only Lands, Tenements or real Eſtates.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 49. He found by his Political A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetick, that we had <hi>anno</hi> 1688, in Stock conſiſting of Gold, Silver and all other things uſually reckoned, Perſonal Eſtates 88 Millions.</p>
               <p>But now <hi>page</hi> 325, to make up his 252 Millions for the young Nobility and Gentry, he reckons, <hi>Lands, Tenements, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments, Perſonal Eſtates,</hi> and computes all at 18 years purchaſe, whether our 88 Millions be not loſt or ſunk by thoſe words, and all included in the 252 Millions, or whether we have 252 Millions and 88 Millions, in all 340 Millions, is not plain, nor how the Kingdoms Capital can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced by his method from 252 Millions to one thouſand Millions.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:34354:63"/>But it is ſuppoſed, the young Nobility and Gentry, will not conclude, that the increaſe from 72 Millions, to 252 Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or to 340 Millions, or what he means to be the ſum total of the Kingdoms ſtock, and Capital Stock, is all owing to foreign traffick, untill it be made out and aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, what Stock or Treaſure, there is now, or was in the Nation 1688 of any conſiderable value that has been gotten from Foreigners, by Foreign Traffick, (excepting our Coin, wrought Plate or Jewels) and that they will wiſely diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between the help that Foreign Trade has afforded towards advancing the value of Lands, by the Conſumption it has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to great quantities of our products abroad, and by Gold and Silver brought home, and what is owing to our natural advantages and improvements made by the labour of our people, and the care and induſtry of their Anceſtors.</p>
               <p>And being the Author has acquainted the Landed-men, <hi>page</hi> 168. <hi>after a long in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into this matter we have reaſons to think that the ſums out upon land ſecurity, has for ſome years been about</hi> 20 <hi>Millions, and and that about one 15th part of the Lands, and other Hereditaments of</hi> England <hi>are in Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage.</hi> Tho it be hoped that the Authors computing faculty has fail'd him in this
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:34354:64"/>at leaſt three quarters of the ſum men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, yet the young Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try whoſe Eſtates are in Mortgage ſhould conclude, that if their Lands can only be diſcharged by the payment of Coin, that the beſt way will be to keep in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what we have, unleſs the Author can give better aſſurance than he has yet propoſed, that if it be ſent out, it ſhall certainly be brought back again with an increaſe.</p>
               <p>As the Author ſeems to conſter every thing that tends to hinder the Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Bullion to be a dangerous Notion, and contrary to the Welfare of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſo what tends to make out that we have decreaſed our Riches by Trade, ſince <hi>an.</hi> 1666, he would have it amount to an affirmation that we have always rather loſt, than got by Trade, and as he makes no ſcruple to ſtretch, ſo not to miſquote words.</p>
               <p>The little Tract he mentions, after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving enumerated the uſes of Gold and Silver, ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>That Jewels, Lead, Tin, or Iron, (tho durable) do not</hi> (ſo well) <hi>deſerve to be eſteemed Treaſure.</hi> The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor prints and reflects <hi>p.</hi> 61. <hi>We can by no means agree with the principles our</hi> Lis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon <hi>Friend would eſtabliſh, That Lead, Tin,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:34354:64"/>or Iron, (tho durable) do not deſerve to be eſteemed Treaſure,</hi> which is grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a miſquotation, ſo groſs as that it ſhall not be imputed to the Author, but to ſome fault in the prints.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 435. The Author returns to the Book mentioned, intituled, <hi>A diſcourſe of Trade and Coin,</hi> and taking notice of ſix pages, in which our good Trades, were only named, that they might be improved and encouraged, and omitting to take notice of fifty pages that immediately fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, where the ſame Subject is purſued upon ſuch Trades, as were ſuppoſed to have an over balance, and that therefore they deſerved more conſideration, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults <hi>p.</hi> 336. <hi>We have here from his own words ſet down the Map he has drawn of our Foreign Traffick, to ſhew, what an ill riſing ground the City of</hi> Lisbon <hi>is to ſtand upon, for one who pretends to give a View of the whole Commercial World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Author had purſued the 50 pages that followed, he would have found, that the Map was drawn larger; and alſo <hi>p.</hi> 153, that, nothing but ſhort hints was deſign'd by that Tract, and no ſuch thing pretended, as to give a Veiw of the Whole Commercial World.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:34354:65"/>As to the City of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> it is ſuppoſed that the City or the ground it ſtands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is as good to take a view, or to make a judgment of Trade, as the Authors <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet</hi> (tho never ſo well furniſhed.) For as good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooks cannot help ſome mens un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in any caſe: So neither all mens underſtanding in all caſes; nor be made a ſecurity againſt all miſtakes. A Famous Author gives an inſtance in <hi>Don Quixot,</hi> who after he had filled his head with Notions of Valour and a great opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of himſelf by reading Books of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry, yet in the purſuit of his Knight Errantry miſtook <hi>Windmills</hi> for <hi>Gyants:</hi> The Authors <hi>Cloſet,</hi> it may be preſumed by his writings, is beſt furniſht with Hiſtory, and Books relating to Politicks and Government, which tho they may have enabled him (at leaſt in his opinion) to correct and direct great Miniſters, and all managers of the Publick Affairs. Yet as the crowding in of ſuch matters with his diſcourſes about Trade could not be, without perplexing his thoughts; ſo that may be the occaſion he has made ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſtakes in his computations and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions about Trade,</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:34354:65"/>Tho learning ought to be admired as a great advantage to them that have it, yet as the reading of Books only never made a compleat Lawyer, or Phyſician, ſo not a compleat Merchant. There being in all profeſſions, a practical or Mechanick part, which cannot be reached but by the help of Experience. Tho the Author takes notice of ſome books he has in his Cloſet upon the Subject of Trade, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, <hi>Britannia Languens</hi> and Mr. <hi>Fortreys</hi> which have many good and true Notions and Obſervations, yet it appears that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, has made little uſe of them, for they not agreeing with his opinions, he only picks out one weak paſſage of each, and paſſes by the Subſtantial part in Silence; deſpiſing all Information as well as Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pericence, and therefore, it ſhould not be admired that there are ſuch contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions in his Notions; as they refer one to another, or to the practical part; or that he ſhould in his computations run into Errors, and Miſtake, Loſs for Gain, or the Dr. ſide for the Creditor ſide.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:34354:66"/>Page 210.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We ſhall endeavour to ſhew that general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeaking, by whatever the returns are more worth than the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity exported, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo much a gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er let the Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be Periſhable or not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Page 219.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We agree ſo far with that Mr. P—when we ſpeak of Trade in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, the gain is ſo much only, as the Nation doth not conſume of the Imports, but either lays up in commodities in Specie, or converts into money or ſome ſuch adequate Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe two Paragraphs are here taken notice off, not only becauſe they ſtand in direct oppoſition, but to diſcover how his miſtaken Notion, <hi>p.</hi> 210. hath lead the Author, into a way of reckoning Loſs for Gain.</p>
               <p>Suppoſing one Million of our Coin (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter converted into Bullion) be ſent to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> and laid out there in Silks and Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins, another Million to <hi>Fraence,</hi> and laid out in Wines, another Million to <hi>Spain,</hi> and laid out there in Fruit: and that all
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:34354:66"/>theſe goods are brought home ſafe, and ſold by the Importers to our own people at <hi>Cent per Cent</hi> profit, and afterwards by the Retailers, with good profit to them, and that none of the ſaid Goods are re-exported, but all ſpent at home.</p>
               <p>According to the Authors Notion, <hi>p.</hi> 210. and way of reckoning, here muſt be three Millions got to the Nation, which is ſo far on the contrary, that by ſuch a Trade here would be three Millions loſs; for the Gold or Silver, which would have been a laſting durable Stock to the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if it had been kept here, will by ſuch a Trade be conſumed; and what brought in, be in the Dreyns, or on the Dunghill, in a ſhort time, and not in being to make any amends for the decreaſe of our Gold and Silver.</p>
               <p>The Author cannot object that this opinion of his <hi>p.</hi> 210, ought not to be extended to Gold or Silver exported, nor periſhable Commodities ſpent at home, becauſe he has uſhered it in with a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, <hi>p.</hi> 209. which explains the matter, and <hi>p.</hi> 210. with a general condemnation of all opinions to the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:34354:67"/>And as he has in his Computations in ſeveral places miſtaken Loſs for Profit, ſo in other places, the Debtor ſide, for the Creditor ſide, in making up his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, in computing the Stock of the Nation, and gain by foreign Traffick.</p>
               <p>P. 167. <hi>That ſuch Stock as was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Money, Plate, Jewels,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by degrees into other Countrys partly to maintain the War, and partly to pay what we have been over balanced in Trade, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our Loſses at Sea; and in its ſtead, we have here at home, Stock of another kind, that is Credits on the publick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. 168. <hi>So that there was a Sum exiſting only in Credit, publick or private, amounting to Thirty four Millions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If there be 34 Millions owing (tho' it is hoped it is not now above half ſo much) the words <hi>exiſting in Credit</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick or private will not excuſe its being a Debt either to Natives or Foreigners. And if ſo, then it ſtands on the wrong ſide, to be called a <hi>Stock</hi> or the Stock of the Nation, which with his miſtakes in Computing the gain made by Foreign Traffick, and the Wealth of the Nation, already taken notice of, may ſufficiently demonſtrate, that the Author doth not go by any good rule in his Computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:34354:67"/>His Reflections begun <hi>P.</hi> 327. have no Foundation; but upon concluſions made upon premiſes of his own Coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: for in the tract he mentions, there are no ſuch aſſertions as he inferrs, the Sums that are there put down, being but ſuppoſed, as ground for an inquiry, to find out what Bullion had been Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Exported or Conſumed at home; if they had been altogether Fictitious, yet being offered only in order to find out the truth, it had been no more than what is uſually practis'd in the like Caſes; but they are ſo far from being ridiculous as this Author repreſents them, that if out of the account he has ſtated, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate 17,400,000 <hi>l.</hi> on his Article of the <hi>French</hi> Trade, which according to the Print ſhould be but 12600000 <hi>l.</hi> at 700000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> for 18 years, whereas he reckons 30,000,000, which is from his own fancy, and abating more 3 Millions on the article for Silver-Lace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no time prefixt for that, and account the Importation of Bullion at 600000 <hi>l per an.</hi> for 40 years, as there mentioned; what will remain conſumed of our old Stock is Nine Millions, which it may be feared, does not differ much from the truth of the Caſe, as for what he Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:34354:68"/>from <hi>P.</hi> 84. That cannot juſtifie his Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation of 30 Million, on the <hi>French</hi> trade, unleſs he can make out, that the words, <hi>Vaſt quantities of Gold and Silver,</hi> muſt ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie a Million at leaſt, and that nothing of the over balance of the Trade of one Country can be ſatisfied by any Exchange or Circulation of the Product of Goods ſent to, or from another Country, which will ſtrike at the root of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, and therefore it's ſuppoſed he will not offer to maintain that point, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on what he there adds to juſtifie his reflections.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 329. <hi>There is nothing here ſtrain'd, and what we have laid down as an undeniable Concluſion from his own Premiſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From which it may be obſerved, That a miſcomputation of 20 Millions is no ſtretch with the Author, and that he cannot forbear, running into a heat, when any thing comes in his way, that tends to make us ſenſible of the uſefulneſs and ſtate of the Nation in reference to our Coin, which cannot ariſe, from any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern he can have, that it is decreaſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he has poſitively aſſerted, <hi>That Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is no more at bottom, than Counters to reckon with:</hi> therefore it muſt be from a fear, that the door ſhould be ſhut to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:34354:68"/>its Exportation, that we may not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the reſt that is left, for which finding himſelf at a loſs for good arguments to Silence his oppoſers, he makes uſe of his Reflections, for which, as he doth not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſo no provocations were given him in the tracts he mentions.</p>
               <p>But the Author having given ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in ſome Paragraphs, <hi>P.</hi> 215, and 380 onwards, that he has now at laſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died ſomething of the A B C of Trade, upon which a general knowledge may be better grounded, by reaſoning from Matter, and Things, and what is uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſed in the courſe of Trade, than from reaſoning by Figures, or drawing concluſions from Schemes, Calculations, or Aſſertions, that have no good Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations; therefore an Examination of ſome of thoſe Paragraphs, may be of uſe to bring the matters in diſpute nearer to an accommodation.</p>
               <p>P. 215. <hi>That the bulk of this Nation's Trade, did amount to about</hi> 10 <hi>Millions</hi> per ann. <hi>and that to gain yearly two Millions there muſt be</hi> 20 per Cent. <hi>profit by Trade in general, whereas the Merchants think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves happy with with a Clear and Conſtant gain of</hi> 12 per. Cent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:34354:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>The Author does not diſtinguiſh how much of the 10 Millions, ſhould be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned Exported, and how much impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, therefore the proportions ſhall be taken to be, according to the Calculation mention'd in the preceeding part of this diſcourſe 4 Millions Exported, 6 Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Imported <hi>an.</hi> 1688, in order to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, whether this be a good argument, that two Millions were gotten the year 1688 as the Author would have it.</p>
               <p>All Computations of gain on Foreign Trade, muſt be calculated upon the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſment, or firſt coſt of the Goods ſent out, the 6 Millions brought home, is not a new disburſment, but a continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the firſt 4 Millions, in order to bring home returns to make profit by what was ſent out. As the adventure cou'd not be over, nor the accounts adjuſted till the returns were brought home, ſo the gain can only be computed upon the 4 Millions ſent out, which at 20 <hi>per. cent.</hi> amounts to but 800000 <hi>l.</hi> and unluckily abates by the Author's own Calculation 1,200,000 <hi>l.</hi> of the two Millions, he would have underſtood, to be yearly gotten by Trade, unleſs the Author will alter his account, and reckon 43 <hi>per cent.</hi> gain to the Nation, on all their Exports,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:34354:69"/>tho he ſeems to infer, that the Merchants got but 12 <hi>per Cent.</hi> as the Author makes out, <hi>p.</hi> 216. <hi>As for Example, a parcel of goods ſent hence for</hi> Virginia, <hi>may fetch ten hogſheads of Tobacco, in which the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant may gain only at the rate of ten</hi> per Cent. <hi>but when this Tobacco, is Shipt again for</hi> Amſterdam, <hi>in the freight backward and forward, and outward gain, and in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactury of goods ſent, when the laſt return comes to be made, all parties concern'd will be found to have got among them</hi> 20 per Cent. <hi>and much more reckoning from the prime Value of the Commodities exported.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Paragraph intended to make out by example, how the Nation may get 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> and the Merchant but 10 <hi>per Cent.</hi> only ſhews how Merchants, Owners, Seamen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may get 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, by our Goods or Coin, changing of hands: But not that there was made any addition to the Stock, Wealth, or Riches of the Nation, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be made by Foreign Trade, unleſs ſome Specie or Commodity from abroad be brought in, which may deſerve to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd Riches. And as this example does not juſtifie the aſſertion, ſo it is not comprehenſive enough to diſcover where
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:34354:70"/>the miſtake lies. Becauſe it does not take in all the ſteps which fuch Trades take, therefore it ſhall be put a little larger, which may afford arguments from exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to confirm what has been ſaid, That tho by the bulk of Foreign Trade we have had great conveniencies and advantages, that we have not made thereby any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to the Wealth, Riches or Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Nation.</p>
               <p>Suppoſing 10 pieces of our ordinary Cloath, to be ſent out to <hi>Virginia,</hi> which uſually contain 32 yards, and take up about 90 <hi>l.</hi> of our Wooll each, which ſhall be (computed as ſome time it has been, worth) 2 <hi>d. per</hi> pound, which is 4 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> The Wages of all ſorts of People, through whoſe hands it paſſes before it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated, and comes to <hi>Blackwell-Hall,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to about 7 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> which makes 12 <hi>l.</hi> thoſe Cloaths may be juſtly eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Owners Wealth, and an addition to the National Stock, all ariſing from our Products and Labour, (unleſs ſome inconſiderable foreign ingredient be uſed, which is uſually alſo procured by our Products, and therefore doth not well deſerve a diſtinction) theſe 10 pieces of Cloaths bing dyed, finiſhed, Shipt off
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:34354:70"/>for <hi>Virginia,</hi> may coſt or be valued in, with all charges, 150 <hi>l.</hi> and accordingly they are eſteem'd, by the perſon that ſends them out. Being arrived at <hi>Virginia,</hi> they are ſold or truckt off for 50 Hogſheads of Tobacco, which being arrived in <hi>England,</hi> the Owner pays 50 <hi>l.</hi> to the Maſter for freight of his Cloath outward, and for his Tobacco brought home, and 400 <hi>l.</hi> for Cuſtom, Impoſts, Lighteridge, Whar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fadge, Cartage, Porterage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> before he can get his Tobacco into his Ware-houſe. If he ſell his 50 Hogſheads for 750 <hi>l.</hi> he is not only re-imburſt of his 600 <hi>l.</hi> disburſt for Coſt and Charges, but gets 150 <hi>l.</hi> to himſelf for his Adventure and Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. Then if the ſaid Tobacco be ſpent at home, it goes from hand to hand to the laſt Conſumer, to be reduced to Smoak.</p>
               <p>By this it may appear as well as by the Inſtances produced by the Author, that the gains particular perſons make by ſuch Trades, is by our Riches changing hands, and not by any Riches gotten from Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners; and that tho ſuch Trades do not afford any increaſe of Wealth, yet great conveniencies and advantages, by the incouragement ſuch Trades give to
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:34354:71"/>induſtry &amp; increaſe of people, becauſe they afford a livelihood to multitudes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the imployment given to Ships and Seamen, in which the ſtrength of the Nation conſiſts, and the ſupport they afford towards the publick charge of the Government by Duties; and to the land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men by the conſumption of their Wooll, which being over and above what we wanted for our own uſe, muſt have lain upon their hands and have periſhed at home, if exportation had not occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the taking it off, and working it up; theſe advantages make a ſufficient amends to the Nation for the loſs of the Cloath, which is turned into Smoak; by which example it may alſo appear that the ſpring of ſuch Trades is from the hopes of gains expected by the particular perſons that ingage in them; our Products, the Matter to work upon; our People, the Agents to improve and make ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts valuable; our Coin, the principal and moſt neceſſary engine or inſtrument, by paſſing from hand to hand: In order to get that, the Materials are ſold, the Manufacturers work, and the Merchants adventure.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:34354:71"/>If ſuch Tobacco be not conſumed at home but re-exported, unleſs Gold and Silver, or ſome durable Commodities be brought in returns of it, or for the freight, ſuch Trades cannot make any addition to the Treaſure of the Nation, by any thing gotten from foreigners.</p>
               <p>Which example of Cloaths ſent out, and Tobacco brought home, may be applyed to the bulk of our other Trades, and to moſt of the exportations and importa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to and from the Plantations; for though we have great advantages from the labour of the people in thoſe parts, by the conveniency of exchanging Goods we can well ſpare, for others we more want or deſire, and by the large an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual income which is paid towards the ſupport of the Publick Charge by the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties on ſuch Goods, and that by the re-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of many of thoſe Products, we have an additional conveniency, by a freſh imployment given to our Ships and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and by exchanging ſuch Goods abroad, for others, yet it doth not appear that we have, or can get Treaſure by the Plantations, unleſs it be brought from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in return of ſome of thoſe Goods re-exported, or from <hi>Jamaica,</hi> or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:34354:72"/>Plantation when they have got it from the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> which it cannot be preſumed, ever amounted to one quarter part of what the Author computes, but the conveniencies aforementioned are ſo conſiderable, that the Plantations and thoſe Trades deſerve all encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>The reſt of his long diſcourſe under the Title, <hi>of the Plantation Trade,</hi> is made up of ſuch variety of matter, that it looks like a collection out of all his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary, as well as out of the Schemes he mentions. He did well to direct it to the young Gentlemen, <hi>p.</hi> 194. for his dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and inſtructions for the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Plantations are ſuch, that it would require an age to make ſuch alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in the preſent Settlements there, as may be neceſſary to make room for the putting of them in practice, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering them feaſible.</p>
               <p>The Authors Computations of the Traffick to the <hi>Eaſt Indias</hi> are not only very confuſed and uncertain, but alſo ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to objections as to matter of Fact.</p>
               <p>In his <hi>Eſſay on the Eaſt India Trade, p.</hi> 54. he ſays,</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:34354:72"/>
                  <hi>I have before divided the</hi> 400,000 l. <hi>prime coſt ſent into</hi> India, <hi>into two parts,</hi> viz. <hi>half for foreign Exportation, and the other half for home Conſumption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>The returns of</hi> 200,000 <hi>l. in time of Peace may proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly yield at abroad</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>l.</hi> 800,000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>The returns of</hi> 200,000 <hi>in time of Peace might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably yield at home</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>800,000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Total</cell>
                        <cell>1600,000</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But we muſt take notice, that the</hi> 1200,000 l. <hi>profit ſuppoſed in time of Peace to ariſe from this Trade, did not all of it accrue to the adventurers in the company, but was Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal, and divided amongſt many thouſands of the people; the Merchants who at the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies Sales bought Goods for Exportation, had their ſhare, and the Retailers here had their proportion in the gains, which this traffick in the whole might be computed to produce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And particularly for their ſhare in the</hi> 600000 l. <hi>ſuppoſed to be gain'd by our own Conſumption, in time of Peace, by this Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick: There came in to the King for his Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:34354:73"/>Owners of Ships, ſuch as got by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualling them; Seamen for Wages, and laſtly, Factors and Servants both abroad and at home.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The gain made abſtractedly by the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, has never been invidious. If their whole Stock be computed from the beginning to this day, it will be found by their Dividends, that they have not one year with another divided</hi> 20 per Cent. <hi>which, conſidering the length and hazard of their Voyages, is not a profit to be envyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 377, 388. The Author Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſes upon this Computation, and now ſays there was 500000 <hi>l.</hi> annually expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that it brought back in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities the value of 1800000 <hi>l.</hi> when it comes to the 2 <hi>d.</hi> 3 <hi>d.</hi> or 4th hands, and that he never meant that the Goods a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to ſo much at the Sale, and therefore that he was miſunderſtood.</p>
               <p>But it is more probable that he miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood himſelf, for his whole diſcourſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make out what a great addition of Wealth was made to the Nation by the <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Trade, the gain made by the Retailers or Venders of thoſe Commodities to the 2<hi>d.</hi> 3<hi>d.</hi> or <hi>4th.</hi> hand, or the thouſands he mentions, can no more be reckoned an addition to the Stock or Wealth of the Nation, than the gain made by <hi>the Chand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:34354:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>in <hi>London,</hi> when they ſell Coals to the poor people by the Peck, at ſuch rates as make three pounds <hi>per chaldron,</hi> can be reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned an addition to the Stock or Wealth of the Owners of Coal Pits, when they have ſold them under ten Shillings <hi>per</hi> Chaldron at their Pits.</p>
               <p>It was never doubted, but that many particular perſons have been concerned in this Trade, and that ſome have made great gains to themſelves by it: The only queſtion is, whether that Wealth ſo got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by them be an addition to the Wealth of the Nation, gotten from Foreigners, by Sales abroad, or out of our own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by high prizes on ſuch Goods con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed at home, and whether the ſending out of ſo much Bullion annually to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe ſuch goods, be not giving an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to ſome particular perſons to inrich themſelves, by <hi>ways and means</hi> that are prejudicial to the Body Politick.</p>
               <p>To which queſtion the Authors com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, <hi>p.</hi> 385. is not a ſatisfactory an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, for it doth not make out how the 4500000 <hi>l.</hi> which he owns was annually carried out in Bullion, has been actually brought in again in Bullion, for notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all his arguments to depreciate the value of Gold and Silver, it is inſiſted upon as a good Maxim, and neceſſary to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:34354:74"/>be obſerved, that nothing can make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends to the Nation for <hi>Bullion</hi> expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but <hi>Bullion</hi> imported, generally ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it refers to Trade; neither doth that computation make out, in what Species or Commodities his 680000 <hi>l.</hi> (to which he has now reduced his 1200000 <hi>l.</hi>) was brought into the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or in what it now conſiſts, where it is now to be ſeen, in Gold, Silver or Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, or in what elſe may deſerve to be eſteemed the Treaſure of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore this as well as his other computations of the many Millions gotten <hi>per annum,</hi> by our ſeveral Trades, ought to be taken as duſt thrown in our eyes, to prevent the making of a narrow inſpection into that Trade; and ſo conſequently to hinder the putting of ſome ſtop to the Exportation of Gold and Silver.</p>
               <p>His computation <hi>p.</hi> 381. is ſo different from his former, that it is apparent he makes his eſtimate according to his fancy, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and not from matter of Fact, or Proofs.</p>
               <p>His two firſt Articles are grounded on a ſuppoſition, that we re-export 500,000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> of thoſe Commodities, but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the general knowledge he
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:34354:74"/>pretends to have, <hi>p.</hi> 4. to compute all Exportations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he gives no account upon what information he grounds it, but taking it for granted that accordingly ſo much was ſold at the Sale to perſons, to be Shipt off, and that they were enter'd out at the Cuſtom-houſe, to be exported, yet he cannot be ignorant, that there is a trade practiſed to make Entries of Goods, as if they were to be Shipt off and ſpent abroad, when in truth nothing is deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but to get back the impoſts, which being very conſiderable on the <hi>Eaſt India,</hi> and ſome other goods, when the repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them is ſecured by ſuch Entryes and Shipping of, the goods are too often either not quite carried out of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſoon brought back again, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Law and all endeavours to prevent it; but if any ſuch quantity of thoſe goods be annually fent out and ſpent abroad, the Author muſt alſo make out, that ſuch as were ſold to Strangers, were purchaſed here with Gold and Silver brought in, or that the returns of ſuch as we ſent out, came home in Bullion or ſome ſuch durable Commodity, or elſe ſtill our 450,000 <hi>l.</hi> in Bullion ſent out will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main as a dead loſs upon the Nation; for periſhable goods can make no amends for the Bullion exported.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:34354:75"/>Neither can his three next articles groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon <hi>ſaving,</hi> make us amends by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting the 450,000 <hi>l</hi> ſent out; for all that we can hope for by thoſe, is according to the Authors own opinion, that we may by the expence of thoſe <hi>India</hi> goods, ſave the going out of more Money to our neighbours for Silks, Linen, or what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goods he means.</p>
               <p>The expreſſions in theſe articles are ſo general, that no judgment can be made upon them. If he had ſpecified what ſorts of Silks, Linens, or other goods he means, and from what Countries they are brought, and for what uſe they did formerly ſerve, which he ſaith are now ſupplyed by theſe from <hi>India;</hi> and had made out, that thoſe he means were uſually purchaſed with our Money, and not obtained in return of our goods; then ſuch inquiries might be made as would afford grounds for a determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether we have ſaved any thing according to thoſe articles; but till the matter be fairly ſtated, the Author having ingeniouſly and truely owned in his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay on the <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Trade, <hi>p.</hi> 33. <hi>That Bengalls and ſtained Callicoes, and other Eaſt India goods do hinder the conſumption of Norwich-ſtuffs, Crapes, Engliſh Ratteens, Shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loons, Says, Perpetuanos and Antherines,</hi> which are ſorts of goods that conſume a
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:34354:75"/>great deal of our Wool, and employ great Numbers of our People, it may be preſumed, that tho' the uſe of ſome of theſe goods from <hi>India</hi> may be conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to be allowed, yet that by the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conſumption of them, we have woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded our ſelves at the heart, by hindring the Conſumption of our Wooll, and the imployment of our People, not only on the Woollen Manufacture but on the Silk and Linen alſo, and that the Author has here again run into his uſual error of miſtaking <hi>loſs</hi> for <hi>gain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Fourth and laſt Article of ſaving is grounded upon his two propoſitions laid down in his Eſſay on the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, <hi>P.</hi> 29.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, That it is not the benefit or intereſt of</hi> England <hi>in general, that Wooll ſhould bear a high price in our Markets at home.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, That by a great Conſumption of the Wooll on Manufactures in this Kingdom, the publick will not reap ſuch an advantage as ſome imagine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſubſtance of his arguments to maintain theſe propoſitions are in effect, that it is the intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> that we ſhould ſend out our Money to purchaſe Manufactured Goods in <hi>India,</hi> becauſe they are there cheap, to ſpend them here at
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:34354:76"/>home in the room of our own, that the price of our Wooll and the labour of our people may be brought down, as a good method to make way for the Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Conſumption of more of our woollen goods abroad.</p>
               <p>It was an over-ſight in the Author, not to direct thoſe propoſitions to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the very young Nobility and Gentry, it being unlikely that thoſe paſt their minority, ſhould be perſwaded to purſue them; for upon the firſt view they appear to contradict all our ancient ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Maxims; the Laws to prevent the Importation of all <hi>European</hi> Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured goods, that could be imagined would hinder the Conſumption of our own, being ſtill in force, and thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Exportation of Bullion were in force, till <hi>ann.</hi> 1663, and upon a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Examination the putting in practice ſuch propoſitions would appear ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Intereſt, that unleſs they were firſt convinced, that they ought to impoveriſh themſelves by their own en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, they would find no reaſon to advance them: for as by diminiſhing the price of Wool, they would make an abatement in their Rents, that depend upon the Sale of that Commodity, ſo by falling the price of Labour, occaſion an u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:34354:76"/>Poverty and inability in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to buy their Corn, Cattle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and as it would be impoſſible that the Gold and Silver ſent out to purchaſe ſuch goods, ſhould be brought into the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion again, by the immediate Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch Goods here, ſo the low price to which the Author would have ours re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, that they may be ſold Cheap in Foreign parts, would hinder the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of any by their Sales abroad; for either he means that our Woollen Goods muſt be ſold Cheap abroad, as well as bought Cheap here, or elſe his deſign would be imperfect; and if they ſhould be ſold ſo cheap, as he ſeems inclinable to have them, then their product will all be taken up there to purchaſe the Goods we want from Foreign Parts, and none will be reſerv'd to come in in Bullion, which will not be brought, if other goods be likely to yield a better accompt.</p>
               <p>If we ſhould fall the price of our Wooll and Labour to one half of what the Rates are now, and by that means we ſhould Export more, yet if we muſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume any of them at home (which this Author takes to be inconvenient,) but ſend them abroad to be ſold at very low Rates, in hopes to beat out other
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:34354:77"/>Nations, (which is the ſpecious pretence the Author gives for this Project) it would be a certain loſs while it is putting in practice, (for little would in ſuch caſes be made of our annual Crops and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour) and it has been found by Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that it is eaſier to fall the price of a Commodity, than to raiſe it again, and therefore it may be preſumed that the annual loſs by ſuch low Sales would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for ever, If we ſhould by any ſuch method bring down the price of our Wooll.</p>
               <p>As the Author has often aſſerted in the behalf of other Trades and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, that they ſhould be left to find out their own Channel, and not be Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by <hi>Tricks and Laws</hi> (as he expreſſes it) ſo certainly there is as much or more reaſon, why the price of our Woollen Goods, and Labour of our Manufacturers ſhould not be Fetter'd by ſuch a Trick, or <hi>by Law,</hi> as this propoſed, but left to find out, its own price at the Markets, both at home and abroad, which will be better than to have them regulated, or brought low by this invention: which, to uſe the Author's words, <hi>P.</hi> 53. ought to be taken as a <hi>Whim:</hi> When the Author has diſcover'd where we can ſpend more
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:34354:77"/>of our Woollen Goods abroad than we now do, it will be eaſie to find out a way to Manufacture more at home, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thoſe Markets, which will be much better, than what the Author has propoſed of ſending over Money to <hi>India,</hi> to buy Manufactured Goods there: tho' many ingenious Men have been prevailed with to write ſeveral Treatiſes in favour of this Trade, yet none were ever ſo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with zeal, as to advance ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions as theſe.</p>
               <p>As for the 100000 <hi>l.</hi> the Author has charged as gain made by that Trade up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this laſt ſaving Article, it ought not to be allowed, untill he has better juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his propoſitions, upon which he grounds it, and has ſhewed, what Woollen goods we ſent out, that were ſaved here at home by the Conſumption of thoſe from <hi>India,</hi> to what places they were ſent, and what Gold and Silver or durable Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was brought, in return of them, to make amends for that which was ſent out to purchaſe the <hi>India</hi> Goods.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 363. The Author ſays, <hi>This No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that our Bullion ſhould be kept at home, runs throughiall Mr.</hi> P—'s <hi>Schemes of Trade, and it is the ground of all his rancour to the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Traffick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:34354:78"/>That the Exportation of ſuch great quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Bullion to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> which for many years, before the War, was at leaſt 600000 <hi>l per an.</hi> computing what was ſent by all the Traders thither, and that the Importation of ſuch great quantities of Manufactured Goods that hinder the Conſumption of our own, both abroad and at home, with the many handicraft Wares; that leſſen the imployment of our People, is the ground upon which ſome Men have an ill opinion of ſome branches of this Trade, or <hi>Rancour</hi> (if the Author will have it ſo conſter'd) is agreed.</p>
               <p>But whereas the Author has by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſcatter'd Expreſſions, repreſented ſuch Notions to be new and ſingular, it is hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily, becauſe he has not had time to get better informations.</p>
               <p>As to the Exportation of Bullion as well as Coin: If he look into our Laws, he will find that our Parliaments were all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, till the year 1662, and if upon a a further inquiry, he ſhould be rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd upon what conſiderations that Law was paſt, that permitted the Exportation of Bullion, even that Law will not be any great juſtification of his opinion, and leaſt he ſhould not think that the opinion of thoſe former Parliaments ought to be put
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:34354:78"/>in the Balance with his, he may find al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that King <hi>Charles</hi> the II. and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil were much of the ſame opinion, in the year 1660, when the firſt Charter for incorporating or confirming the Trade to the <hi>Eaſt Indies</hi> paſt, for he will find theſe Clauſes and Reſtrictions in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it ſhall and may be lawful to and for the ſaid Governour and Company, and their Succeſsors, to Ship and Tranſport out of this our Realm of</hi> England, <hi>or Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the ſame, in any of their Voyages to or towards any of the Ports aforeſaid; ſuch foreign Coin of Silver,</hi> Spaniſh <hi>or other foreign Silver or Bullion, as they ſhall bring or cauſe to be brougt into the Realms of</hi> England, <hi>from Ports beyond the Seas, in the ſame Kind, Stamp or Faſhion, which it ſhall have, when they bring it in, or other Form, Stamp or Faſhion to be Coined in our Mints, within our Tower of</hi> London, <hi>at their Pleaſure, ſo as that the whole quantity of Coin or Money by them to be tranſported in any of the ſaid Voyages, do not exceed the value or ſum of Fifty Thouſand Pounds; at any one Voyage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the ſaid Governour and Company of Merchants of</hi> London, <hi>trading into the</hi> Eaſt Indies, <hi>and their Succeſsors in all and every ſuch Voyage as they at any time or times
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:34354:79"/>hereafter ſhall make out of this Realm, by Vertue of this Grant, and Letters Patents, (the first Voyage only excepted) ſhall and will upon every return, which ſhall be made back again into this Realm, or within ſix months next after ſuch return, bring into this our Realm of</hi> England, <hi>from the ſaid</hi> Faſt Indies, <hi>or from ſome part beyond the Seas out of our Dominions, as great or a greater value in Bullion of Gold or Silver reſpectively for every Voyage (the firſt Voyage only excepted) as ſhall, by force of theſe preſents, be tranſported and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out of this Realm, by them, or any of them, in any kind of Silver aforeſaid what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſover, in any of the ſaid Voyages, and that all ſuch Silver, as by vertue of this our Grant and Letters Patents ſhall be Shipt or Loaden by the ſaid Governour and Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or their Succeſſors, to be tranſported out of this Realm, in any of the ſaid Voyages; ſhall from time to time at the ſetting forth of every ſuch particular Voyage, be Shipt or Loaden at the Ports or Havens of</hi> London, Dartmouth, <hi>or</hi> Plimouth, <hi>or at ſome of the ſaid Ports or Havens, and at no other Port or Haven whatſoever, within this our Realm or the Dominions thereof, and that all and every ſuch Silver, as from time to time ſhall be Shiped or Loaden, in the ſaid Ports of</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:34354:79"/>Dartmouth, <hi>or</hi> Plimouth, <hi>or any of them, to be by force of this preſent tranſported out of this our Realm, as is aforeſaid, ſhall from time to time be duely entred by the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomer, Comptrouller, Collectors or any other Officers, to whom it shall appertain, at every ſuch Port or Haven, where the ſame shall happen to be Shipt or Loaden in the Cuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe Books, belonging to the ſaid Ports or Haven, before ſuch time that the ſame shall be Shipped or Loaden to be tranſported as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, without any Cuſtom or Subſidies to be paid for the ſame, and that in like manner all and all manner of Gold and Silver what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, which shall be brought into this our Realm, or any of our Dominions, by the ſaid Governour and Company, or any of them according to the true meaning of this preſent, shall likewiſe be from time, to time, duly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the Cuſtomers, Comptroullers, or Officers of every ſuch Port, Creek or Places where the ſame Gold or Silver shall happen to be unſhiped, or brought to Land: according to ſuch orders as by our Treaſurer of</hi> England <hi>for the time being, ſhall be taken for the entering of the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which limitation of Fifty Thouſand Pound, appears to be agreeable to what was Shipt of, by Licences granted in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Reigns.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:34354:80"/>For it appears by a Manuſcript of good Authority, of which the Author may be better informed at the <hi>Eaſt India</hi>-houſe (if the old Books be not loſt) that there was Shipt off for the carrying on of this Trade.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>An.</hi> 1624 in goods and Bullion —</cell>
                        <cell>68,225 P.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>An.</hi> 1625 in goods and Bullion —</cell>
                        <cell>39,445 P.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>An.</hi> 1626 in goods and Bullion —</cell>
                        <cell>39,381 P.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>An.</hi> 1627 in goods and Bullion —</cell>
                        <cell>75,318 P.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>An.</hi> 1628 in goods and Bullion —</cell>
                        <cell>67,745 P.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>An.</hi> 1629 in goods and Bullion —</cell>
                        <cell>61,000 P.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>And as for the opinion of particular perſons he may be informed, that, when the alteration in the management of this Trade, was firſt attempted, which was ſoon after the year 1666. How Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Thompſon</hi> and others, that were much concerned in the Trade, did oppoſe it, then declaring their opinion, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging of the Trade by ſuch methods would diminiſhour Coin, hinder the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of our own Manufactures, and endanger a diſſolution of the Company, by the Clamours they would bring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:34354:80"/>And ſince it may be ſuppoſed that he admires the <hi>French</hi> Councils (for he ſays <hi>p.</hi> 60. <hi>Such as have not been bred Merchants are as competent Judges as any trading per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever, for it was to the deep Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Miniſters of State,</hi> Richleiu <hi>and</hi> Colbert, <hi>and not to the Merchants, that</hi> France <hi>owes the proſperity, their Trade was lately in, and it was their Wiſdom more than the Induſtry of the Merchants that laid the foundation of it.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Now as to this Trade, the <hi>French Eaſt-India</hi> Company are under ſuch rules and reſtrictions, as that they can neither ſend out any quantity of Gold and Silver, for <hi>India,</hi> nor bring in any Manufactured Goods, that can prejudice thoſe made in <hi>France,</hi> and that no other Nation may bring in any ſuch Goods, they either totally prohibit them, or lay ſuch impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions on them, as amounts to a Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, condemning to be burnt, what are found in any Mans Cuſtody, contrary to ſuch reſtrictions: As if they agreed with the Authors opinion in his <hi>Eſſay on the Eaſt-India Trade.</hi> Page 11. Europe <hi>draws from</hi> India <hi>nothing of ſolid uſe, Materials to ſupply Luxury, and only periſhable Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities; and ſends thither Gold and Silver, which is there buried, and never returns.</hi>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:34354:81"/>But not in his Project, to bring in thoſe from <hi>India,</hi> or <hi>England,</hi> or from any place to be ſpent at home, that they may have the more of their own to Export. And for the States he mentions, their deſigns are alſo to increaſe their Coin, and incourage their own Manufactures, if they permit the Exportation of Coin, when they are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, it ſhall be returned with an increaſe, it ought not to be admitted as a good ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that we ſhould encourage the Exportation of it, when we have no ſuch proſpect; but being the Author ſuggeſts, <hi>p.</hi> 412. that the Conſumption of our Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Goods may be promoted in <hi>Tartary, Japan, China,</hi> and many other places: and ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 419. <hi>Not only our Draperies, courſe and fine may obtain in thoſe Regions, but our other Manufactures and Commodities may be there introduced, with which we may purchaſe, the Goods of one Country for the uſe of another; and ſo carry on a Coaſt Traffick, till at laſt in the Circuit of Trade, a large part of the Goods brought from thence ſhall become the return of our own Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is hoped that the Author may have the glory to bring this about, and ſo by preventing the Exportation of more Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, put an end to all <hi>Rancour</hi> and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:34354:81"/>about this Trade, but ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions have been formerly uſed as a blind, for many have not forgotten, how often ſome Members of the <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Company formerly told King <hi>Charles</hi> in Publick Auditories, <hi>viz. That the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would ingage to ſpend as many Woollen Goods, in</hi> India, China, Japan, <hi>and thoſe parts, as all the Weavers in</hi> England <hi>could make, if they might be protected in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of that Trade, according to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of their Charter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As we ſhould not loſe our hold in that Trade, nor the conveniency of fetching, in our own Ships, Salt-peter, Druggs, Spices, or what elſe, upon an examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be convenient for us, ſeeing the Trade is now ſetled agreeable to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors opinion. <hi>P.</hi> 423. <hi>It is upon theſe Grounds and Principles, that we offer to publick conſideration, Whether it may not be adviſeable, and for the intereſt of</hi> England, <hi>to ſettle the</hi> Eaſt India <hi>Trade, by the Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Authority for ſuch a term of time, and upon ſuch conditions, as shall be thought fair, equal and reaſonable, by the united Wiſdom of the Nation.</hi> It is hoped that ſuch al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations will be made in the management, as may render it moſt advantageous, for which there will be neceſſary (to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:34354:82"/>this Subject with the Authors own words) <hi>p.</hi> 375. <hi>Sounder Heads than ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of us are Maſters of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Author having printed in his <hi>Eſſay on the Eaſt India Trade, p.</hi> 11. <hi>That we bring no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from</hi> India <hi>but materials to ſupply Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and only perishable Commodities,</hi> he ſeems in all his Diſcourſes to be at a great loſs, what to ſay upon that Subject, and if he condemn it, in one page, he diſpenſes with it in the next, and all that can be collected from what he writes about that matter, ſeems to amount to this; That it has got ſuch footing amongſt us, that all that we muſt now do, is, to feed it at the cheapeſt rate, and with all the fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity we can, and for that, propoſes as our beſt way, the ſending of our Money to <hi>India,</hi> to buy materials at the beſt hand; but this reaſoning of his muſt rather pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from his affections for that Trade, than from conſiderations referring to the intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe it is ſuppoſed that if we keep our Coin at home, and by the circulation of it do incourage indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and labour, that we ſhall have of our own Products ſufficient to purchaſe from abroad, what Materials or Commodities we want to ſatisfie luxurious Appetites.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:34354:82"/>To determine what operation or effect, Luxury, or Frugality, will have upon Trade, and to diſcover how much gaining or loſing depends upon it, the quality of ſuch Goods as are the Subject of Trade, muſt be conſidered as well as the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for as a private man, by exchanging Gold and Silver for the like quantity of baſer metals, muſt grow poor, ſo ſhall a Nation that will make it their buſineſs to exchange thoſe Species, or any other va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable, during and laſting Commodities, for ſuch as are periſhable, and of no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance: and as a private man muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come indebted, and grow poor, that ſpends more than his income, ſo a Nation that by a laviſh Conſumption of Foreign Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities at home, occaſion the Importation of Goods from abroad, that exceed in value the produce of what they ſend out.</p>
               <p>Tho the various Tempers, Conditions and Appetites of Men, render it impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to make a definition, what ought to be eſteemed Luxury, or Frugality in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, or where to fix any true Bounds or Limits, becauſe there are many reaſons, why ſome perſons ſhould conſume, and ſpend more than others, not only in value, but of ſome ſort of Goods,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:34354:83"/>that approach nearer to Luxury than others; yet that liberty ſhould not be extended to what may endanger the conſuming of the Treaſure or Publick Stock of the Body Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick: A miſchief that might be prevented without putting an intolerable reſtraint up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mens Appetites, by making a judicious diſtinction not only as to the ſorts of Goods imported, but alſo as to the places from whence they come, and how pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, as abſolutely neceſſary to prevent trading upon uncertain loſing, or deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive terms. As imaginary neceſſities ſhould not lead us into the inconveniencies and deſtruction that attend unbounded Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury, ſo an ill grounded Frugality, ſhould not lead us into the checking of any Trade, that can be carried on by a permutation of Commodities; for as we expect that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations ſhould take off our Goods, ſo they may rationally expect that we ſhould take off theirs, and ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries cannot take off any Goods from us, unleſs we take others from them.</p>
               <p>The greateſt ſecurity that can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed againſt our ſpending too much in Commodities, and what is moſt likely to afford us the advantages expected by frugality, is the promoting the Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our own Products and Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:34354:83"/>for as the uſing of ſuch at home, would prevent the importation of many Goods that are pernicious, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to ſettle the Balance of Trade in our favour, ſo it would encourage the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of all ſorts of Manufactures and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicrafts Wares by our own people, which is the ſureſt way to encreaſe our Wealth, by our annual Crops, and what we have got out of the Bowels of the Earth, and Sea, improved by labour. As that gave birth to our Wealth, ſo the Treaſure or Riches we now have, muſt thereby be preſerved or increaſed; in which the Author, may probably be beſt convinced by obſervations grounded upon his own computation, <hi>p.</hi> 414. where he makes our Wooll impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to amount to 8 Millions annually, to which adding 4 Millions by the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments made by our Mines, of Tin, Iron, Lead, Coals, Allom, and by our fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Trades, and by the Manufacturing of Silk, Cotten and Foreign Materials, and by the making of Handicraft Wares, which as it all amounts to 12 Millions, ſo it is divided of courſe amongſt the Owners of Lands, Labouring Men, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, throw whoſe hands ſuch Goods do paſs, in the way of Trade, Merchants, Shopkeepers, Manufacturers, Owners of
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:34354:84"/>Ships, Seamen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to one more, and to another leſs according to their induſtry, skill, or good fortune, and what each lays up after his expences and out goings are diſcharged, they well eſteem, as their Riches, and ſuch part of that as they lay out and convert into any thing laſting and durable and valuable that remains in the Nation, ought to be eſteemed an addition to the Riches or Wealth of the Nation, which it is viſible by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements of Lands, increaſes of buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Houſes and Ships, and ſome du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Furniture for Houſes, and other uſes, has been annually conſiderable, and as thus our Products are the Original of ſuch Riches, we have got at home; ſo it will appear they are the Original of the Riches that we get from abroad, for what we obtain from Foreigners (the gain made by Factors and Merchants got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from Foreigners in Foreign Parts, or by the imployment of our Ships excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) is in exchange, or for the return of ſuch Goods ſent out, therefore Foreign Trade may rather be ſaid to be a means to encourage and improve the advantages we make by our Labour at home, than the foundation of our Riches; and as it cannot be expected that thoſe that buy,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:34354:84"/>ſell, or diſpoſe of ſuch Goods, or are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therways concerned, ſhould make it their buſineſs to ſtruggle who ſhall get moſt for the Nation, ſo it may be concluded, That all ſuch endeavours amongſt the Traders or Individuals, is, who ſhall have the greateſt ſhare of the twelve Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and that, as no addition can be made to the ſtock of the Nation by any part of the ſaid twelve Millions that is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed at home, but only by ſuch part as is converted into what is laſting and durable, ſo not by ſuch part as is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, unleſs when exchanged for Gold or Silver, or durable Commodities, and ſuch be retained in the Nation, which cannot be expected, as long as by the Prodigal Conſumption at home of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhable Commodities, the Traders may reap more profit by importing them, than by bringing in Gold or Silver, or more profit by Exporting it again, than by Exporting of Goods; upon which it may be concluded, that we have a plain and ſafe way to make annual additions to our Wealth, without adventuring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any dangerous or new way of Trad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, therefore it is preſumed that we had better depend upon our old Foundations and Maxims, and make it our buſineſs
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:34354:85"/>to retain our Gold and Silver, that it may circulate for the promoting of our home Trades, than ſend it abroad, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out better aſſurance (than has yet been given) that it will be brought back in the ſame Species, with an increaſe, and alſo that neither the Government nor Trade ſhall ſuffer by the want of it, during its Progreſs and Circulation from Country to Country; for we may be aſſured that the want of Coin will have the ſame effect, and as certainly decreaſe tho' inviſibly our home Trades and Profeſſions, as the want of Tools, Utenſils, Stock or Engines, will occaſion a decreaſe in the Trades of particular perſons.</p>
               <p>But if the twelve Millions ariſing by our Crops and Labours, which by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence is annually diſtributed, one quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part (it may be ſuppoſed) amongſt the Landed Men, and three quarters part amongſt the Manufacturers, and Traders, be thought too little; though what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages the Landed Men make other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, by their Corn, Cattle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor what gains the Trading Men make by ſelling, retailing, and other dealings, doth not come within this Computation; and it be concluded that to increaſe our gain, we may do well to add to our Exportation
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:34354:85"/>of Goods, the Exportation of our Gold and Silver alſo, that by inlarging our Stock we may encreaſe our Trade, and have more of the advantages, and Conveniences, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, according to our Author's Obſervations, <hi>P.</hi> 373. <hi>Theſe Heads have been the longer dwelt upon, only to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their weak and narrow Notions, who would run all the Treaſure procured by Trade into the Mint, from whence all, above juſt what is neceſsary, will of courſe, and according to late practices; be carried into the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers Cheſt, where it is uſeleſs; whereas if what is more than neceſſary for the Kingdom's uſe, remain in Bulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it might be a productive ſtock abroad, for as Money that Circulates at home, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets Money to private Men, ſo Bullion, Circulating abroad begets Bullion to a Country.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No Objection ſhould be made to this Paragraph if any aſſurance could be given, that our Bullion Exported, would be a Productive Stock abroad, and to beget an increaſe of Bullion, as the Author af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms; but that ought not to be Credited till the Author have writ another Book, to give a more probable demonſtration from what places, or in return of what Goods, we have ſince the year 1673
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:34354:86"/>brought in Bullion, to anſwer for the great quantities Exported, and where it is now to be ſeen, or how we may be ſure it will come in hereafter, if a large Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation be encouraged, for to give the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor his due, tho' he has told us often of vaſt and great gains made by Trade, yet he has not adventured to make out, that we have of late got Gold and Silver, but rather owns it is decreaſed, ſo that there is not one line in this Book to that purpoſe, though many to under-value Gold and Silver, and to render the uſe of it inſignificant, and to perſwade us to be liberal of it.</p>
               <p>By this the Author's laſt mentioned paragraph, it appears that the Author is very much afraid of having too much Bullion carried into the Mint, but if he had examined how little has been carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in of Foreign Coins, or which we may be aſſured was Foreign Bullion, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of late, but many years before the War, or what proſpect there is now, that the Mint will have too much, he would have found cauſe to have excuſed repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting his fears upon that Subject; and as the Author has diſcover'd his miſtake in theſe matters, ſo in what he ſaith as to the Trade of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers,</hi> who uſually
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:34354:86"/>pine as much to have mony lockt up in their Cheſts, as others do, becauſe they have none at their Command, therefore it is probable that he meant <hi>Monſters</hi> not <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers,</hi> of which it may be ſuppoſed there are very few of that kind, and that the <hi>Silver</hi> Coin hoarded up, is but little, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Gold</hi> ſome men may keep by them; for what was lately practis'd, when our Coin was ſo clipt and abuſed, cannot well be ſuppoſed to be practiſed now, becauſe the cauſe is removed.</p>
               <p>Tho it may be difficult to underſtand what the Author means by what he has writ about the <hi>French</hi> Trade, <hi>page</hi> 347 onwards, for firſt he tells his Reader <hi>(as a piece of news,)</hi> that we had the Balance of our ſide, till the <hi>French</hi> begun to mind Trade, and that, after they laid high Duties and Prohibited the uſe of the <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Goods, that our dealings there, begun to grow very diſadvantageous to this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Then adds, tho by our Trade in general, we exported three Millions and a half, of which he owns, much was in Money, and imported 6 Millions and a half, as valued here, yet he concludes his long Paragraph, <hi>p.</hi> 348. <hi>If our whole Exports are about three Millions, and our Imports are ſix Millions and a half, it
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:34354:87"/>follows that tho our Imports do exceed our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, three Millions, it is ſo far from being an argument that we loſe three Millions yearly by the over Balance, that quite contrary, if three Millions and a half will purchaſe ſix Millions and a half, we are inriched by what is commonly reckoned an over Balance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ſuppoſed that what has been already ſaid, about making computations relating to Trade, may diſcover, how inconſiſtent theſe aſſertions are, with any true or ſafe Rules, for computing the gain on Trade as it refers to a Nation; and that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon but the Author can reconcile his own opinions about the <hi>French</hi> Trade, for in his computations in his <hi>Eſſay on the Eaſt India</hi> Trade, <hi>p.</hi> 17. he computes that we got by the <hi>French</hi> Trade, from the year 56, to the year 1688. Now he ſays that after <hi>Richlieu</hi>'s Miniſtry, (which ended about the year 1657,) by the laying of high Duties on our Goods, <hi>our dealing grew ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſadvantageous,</hi> and then in the end of the next Paragraph, <hi>That we were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched by what is commonly reckoned an over Balance againſt us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:34354:87"/>But till the Author have explained his meaning, as to the <hi>French</hi> Trade, the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of others ſhould be followed, which are, That the <hi>French</hi> had, for many years, an over Balance, of about one Million <hi>per annum,</hi> and that there was carried from us to Balance that Trade, and ſpent there by our Travellers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in all about 700000 <hi>l. per annum</hi> in Bullion, and being the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor has obſerved <hi>p.</hi> 138. <hi>That we took from the Sound,</hi> as many Goods as coſt 400000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> and that for the moſt of them we ſent out Money in Specie, or Bills of Exchange, which Bills upon an examination will be found inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that were drawn for thoſe parts, and at all times much the ſame thing as Money; and having alſo own'd, that we did uſually ſend out 500000 <hi>l.</hi> to <hi>India</hi> (which others compute to be 600000 <hi>l.</hi> and that we conſumed much Bullion for wrought Plate, Fringe, Lace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and being it is ſuppoſed he will own, that ſome has always gone, and will in probability go ever out, for ſome other Trades, or occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; it is hoped that he will in his next Book apply his thoughts more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſhew from whence, and from what places, Bullion did formerly come in, or may hereafter, to ſatisfie any ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:34354:88"/>and Demand, or ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption as he may gueſs our Trades, as now carried on, may require, leaſt by endeavouring to enlarge our Trade by ſending out all the Bullion that may come in, we endanger the loſs of the Good Trades, we have, by graſping at too much.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page.</hi> 219. The Author ſays, <hi>We agree ſo far with Mr.</hi> P — <hi>when we ſpeak of Trade in general, the gain is ſo much only, as the Nation did not conſume of the Imports, but either lays up in Commodities, in Specie, or converts into Money, or ſome ſuch adequate Treaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This condeſcention is not only, very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging, but ſo material, that a ſhort en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry what Species or Commodities are now in the Nation, or were <hi>anno</hi> 1688 brought in by foreign Trade, that may be eſteemed durable Treaſure, or adequate Treaſure, and in what proportion ſuch Treaſure has increaſed, will very much conduce to reſolve all diſputes about riches gotten by foreign Trades.</p>
               <p>All agree that our Gold and Silver, was brought in by foreign Trade, of which Species, the Author computes, <hi>p.</hi> 36, That we had in the Nation <hi>an.</hi> 1688, the ſum of 18, 500, 000 <hi>l.</hi> of what was
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:34354:88"/>coined from the beginning of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s Reign 1558, which makes about 130 years, and is in proportion to near 150000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> the ſtock that was in the Nation when that Princeſs began her Reign, and what ſhe got from the <hi>Spaniards</hi> by force of Arms, being thrown in, to make it hold out to that proportion; and as for Bullion that was brought in and converted into wrought Plate; and Jewels, that may be preſumed remain'd in the Nation, if half as much be reckoned, that is 75000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> than our annual gain by foreign Trade in thoſe years, and in theſe Species <hi>that was laid up in the Nation and not conſumed,</hi> amounts to 225000 <hi>l. per annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if the Author will not go ſo far back, but would rather take his meaſures, from the year 1660 to 1688, which are his 28 years of our great and flouriſhing Trade. <hi>Page</hi> 33, 34, 35, He makes the coinage account in thoſe 28 years to be of Gold and Silver. 10,700,000</p>
               <p>Out of which he juſtly abates as not brought in by Trade, or decreaſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:34354:89"/>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Coined out of <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Money</cell>
                        <cell>100,0000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For Gold being coined over and over</cell>
                        <cell>1,500,000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For hammer'd Money melted down</cell>
                        <cell>1,700,000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For milled money conſumed or exported</cell>
                        <cell>2000000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>06200000</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4500000</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Which 4500000 <hi>l.</hi> increaſe of our Coin in thoſe 28 years, is near about the ſame proportion of 150000 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> as computed in the former Reigns, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding half ſo much more for the increaſe of Plate and Jewels as before, will make the ſame increaſe of 225000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> what other Commodities were brought into the Nation in thoſe 28 years, or in the 130 years by Trade, and not conſumed, <hi>but either laid up in Commodities, in Specie, or converted into Money, or ſome ſuch ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate Treaſure,</hi> that may come within the Authors own deſcription of gain, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be exactly compted.</p>
               <p>But upon the peruſal of the Book of Rates, where it is ſuppoſed that all the Commodities we deal in, are enumerated (excepting ſome few that are entred <hi>ad
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:34354:89"/>valorem</hi>) and the Bills of Entries, from the Cuſtom-houſe, where all that are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported are comprehended, there doth not appear any good reaſon to ſuppoſe that we ever did import into this Nation, of Iron, Braſs, Copper, or of other ſorts of Goods that were laſting and durable, or other ways adequate to Treaſure, the value of 100000 <hi>l. per annum</hi> but (to make up even Money) 175000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> ſhall be computed, which with the Gold and Silver, and Jewels, makes 400000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> tho much of the Iron, Copper, Braſs or the like is uſually in a ſhort time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to ſuch uſes, as depreciates its ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal value, and only a ſmall proportion improved.</p>
               <p>Moſt other ſorts of Goods brought in from Foreign parts, as they are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of duration, ſo they would not be brought in, but in Expectation of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Sale and Conſumption, thoſe for eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drinking are ſoon reduced to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and thoſe for Apparel, have uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but a ſhort Exiſtence, thoſe for a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Manufacture, are ſoon apply'd to thoſe uſes; and if any Stock of ſuch Goods have remained for any time in the hands of the Trader, it was not becauſe they were kept for an addition to the Stock
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:34354:90"/>of the Nation, but becauſe the Markets would not take them off, the gains of Trading men, not ariſing from keeping their Goods, but by buying, ſelling, chop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and changing, wherefore there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be any Stock of ſuch Goods in the Nation, but what lie for want of Sale, or Conſumption, or to ſupply the Markets.</p>
               <p>Tho' it be not doubted but that in moſt of thoſe Twenty Eight years we proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly brought in 500000 <hi>l.</hi> in Silver and 100000 <hi>l.</hi> in Gold <hi>per an.</hi> by our good Trades, and that the Clippings of the ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer'd Money in thoſe years, which was either Coin'd or Exported amounted to a conſiderable Sum, yet it appears by this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, that ſuch was the Conſumption of our Bullion before it came to the Mint, or ſoon after; that <hi>ann.</hi> 1688 there was no more but in proportion to 150000 <hi>l. per ann.</hi> remaining by the Author's account, and how our hammer'd Money was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed even in thoſe years, has been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready offered to conſideration, and that what thus remained was rather a turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of old Money into new, than an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to our Stock.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:34354:90"/>As by theſe enquiries, which are moſt grounded on the Author's own Compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and therefore may the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him, it may appear that he was miſtaken in this account of two Millions <hi>per ann.</hi> which he ſays was added, to the Stock of the Nation, by thoſe Trades he mentions, ſo it may confirm what has been ſaid, that, tho' we may eaſily conſume our Coin, yet that it will not be regain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without a great deal of difficulty, and length of time; for which as good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils will be neceſſary to lay a Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by good Laws, ſo the induſtry of the Merchants, that ſuch Laws may have a good effect: For, not withſtanding the Author's Opinion, <hi>P.</hi> 69, the gaining of Gold or Silver by Trade, doth wholly depend upon their Skill, Induſtry, and Courage, by adventuring our Products or other Goods to procure it from abroad by their dealings with Foreigners in Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Parts, for all Buying, Selling, Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing, Lending, Trading, or <hi>Tricking</hi> at home, can only afford gains to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons, by our Riches changing hands, and all new Projects, and new Diſcoveries, will be more liable to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointments, than what can be feared from the Exportation of our Products, if
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:34354:91"/>Trade be ſo managed, as that we may not be under a neceſſity to ſend out our Gold and Silver as faſt as it is brought in from abroad.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 375. The Author ſays <hi>That he has choſen all along to ſet up a different Structure</hi> (from Mr. <hi>P</hi>—) <hi>and to propoſe another Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis,</hi> in which he has ſaid what is true, for his Notions are not only very different from his, but from what has been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly practiſed, and alſo will be dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be now purſued.</p>
               <p>It would take up too much time, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all the ſtrange Arguments he has offered to ſupport this <hi>new ſtructure</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore only ſome few ſhall be taken notice of, as an addition to the obſervations al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made.</p>
               <p>Pag. 415. <hi>That Wool ſhould bear a good price is moſt certainly the intereſt of the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, but then this muſt come in ſome na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural courſe, for ſuppoſing that by a rot of Sheep its value ſhould be advanced to two Shillings</hi> per Pound, <hi>would this make for the intereſt of Land? moſt certainly not; no more than to have Wheat brought from</hi> 30 s. <hi>to</hi> 3 l. per quarter, <hi>by Blights, or an ill Seaſon, but it would be well for Land here, if a dearth abroad ſhould occaſion ſuch a call for our Grain, as to bring it to that Price.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="175" facs="tcp:34354:91"/>Certainly the Author doth think that the Landed Men, may be very eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impoſed upon, and that they do not underſtand what is their true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, or how to find out a fallacy in an argument, or elſe it is not probable he would have offered them, what he doth in this Paragraph? How can a rot of Sheep, or a Blight of Corn, which may happen ſometimes, and by the hand of Providence (if it do advance the price of Wooll and Corn for a year, or the like) be brought as an inſtance, to perſwade the Landed Men, that it is their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to ſend their Money to <hi>India</hi> to buy Manufactured Goods, to be ſpent here at home, in the room of their own, in order to bring down the price of Wooll and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Is there no difference between what may happen by Chance or Providence, and cannot be prevented, and what a Man does voluntarily, conſtantly, and freely, on a ſuppoſition that it is his intereſt ſo to do? If he will give an inſtance that may make for his purpoſe, in this caſe, he muſt ſhew the Landed Men, that it is their intereſt to be conſtantly ſending their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to <hi>Holland</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> to buy Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Goods or Corn to be frequently Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported here, in order to keep down the
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:34354:92"/>price of Wooll, Corn, and Labour, that we may be forced to Export our own Woollen goods, and Corn, and by beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down the Markets abroad, to gain the whole Trade abroad to our ſelves, for the Objection that we had better inrich the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> than our Neighbours may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, but it is ſuppoſed the Sophiſtry of this argument will plainly appear, and what is deſigned by it; by theſe hints.</p>
               <p>In the ſame Page he ſaith, he is able to maintain, <hi>That the publick of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try can by no manner of means be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to get ſo much by what Woollen Goods are conſumed in the Nations as by what is carried to Foreign Markets.</hi> It is not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but he may maintain this, for it has been all along owned, that we make no addition to our Riches, by what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed at home, but it does not therefore follow, that we muſt ſend out our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to buy Goods to be ſpent here at home in the room of them, that we may ſpend none at all, <hi>which is his Topick,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be denied, but that if by good Husbandry we ſhould make nine Thouſand pieces of Cloath ſerve for our own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, inſtead of Ten Thouſand, that have been uſually ſpent, but that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:34354:92"/>One Thouſand pieces will be ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and bring back ſomething.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 417 the Author declares he has an ill Opinion of <hi>Crapes, Serges, Stuff, &amp;c.</hi> by which <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may be meant near half the Woollen Goods we make, and that it would be moſt advantageous for us to make only <hi>courſe Cloaths and Stuffs for the Markets abroad.</hi> By Stuffs it is ſuppoſed he means thoſe that are very courſe, that they may not hinder the Conſumption of <hi>India</hi> Goods, then adds, <hi>That it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly true, that a riſe in its value of a penny</hi> per <hi>pound proceeding from Foreign ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, does more inrich the body of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than a riſe of three pence</hi> per <hi>pound oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd only by our own Conſumption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tho' the truth of this aſſertion ſhall not be diſputed at preſent, yet it ought not to weigh much with the Landed Men, before the Author has made out, where we ſhall ſpend more of our Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Goods, than now we do, how we ſhall bring the people in Foreign parts, as well as at home, to be fond of theſe <hi>courſe Cloaths</hi> and <hi>courſe Stuffs,</hi> and oblige them to chooſe and ſpend them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Goods from <hi>India,</hi> becauſe thoſe may be much finer, and in time much cheaper, than ſuch Cloaths or Stuffs, tho'
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:34354:93"/>the price of Wooll ſhould fall to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>But to comfort the landed men, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor tells them in the ſame page, <hi>That Wooll is a Rich and Noble Material, capable of ſuch improvements, that it may be turned an</hi> 100 <hi>ways to increaſe the wealth and Trade of England,</hi> and then gives an inſtance of one of thoſe 100 ways grounded upon hopes: <hi>That they may ſpend great quantities of theſe Goods in</hi> India, <hi>if agood Settlement of that Trade were made,</hi> which being done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Authors own deſire, <hi>page</hi> 423, it would be a great proof that theſe his Aſſertions are well grounded, if he would leave us our Bullion or Coin, and take with him as a Cargo for his intended Voyage, a good round quantity of our Woollen Goods; or if not, that, he would tell us, not only how our Wooll ſhall be conſumed, but how the poor (who dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſe upon us, ſhall be imployed, if all the ſorts of ſtuffs, as well as the Silk and Linen Manufactures, as propoſed in his <hi>Eſsay on the Eaſt India Trade,</hi> be laid aſide? How then it will be in the power of Magiſtrates or Overſeers, (or be it a Corporation ſet up with a ſtock, for the purpoſe, to give them imployment.) On what ſhall they be kept to work, when
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:34354:93"/>ſo many more ſhall be added, that were imployed in thoſe Manufactures, to the great number we have already, in all Towns and Corporations.</p>
               <p>But after all, the writer of theſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, is ſenſible, that objections may be made to all computations, of the Coin, and Trade of the Nation, but however he can truly ſay for himſelf, that what he has writ, is grounded upon the beſt informations he could get, and with a good deſign, that ſuch care may be taken in the managment of our Trade for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that we may increaſe our Coin, which ſeems to be abſolutely neceſſary, leaſt the Body Politick be reduced to an Hectick condition, while we are caſting of Figures, or depending on the Authors Projects: And if after this fair and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial examination, he is conſtrain'd to differ in opinion, from the Author of <hi>Ways and Means;</hi> yet ſeeing his not affixing his name to his Book, is a ſufficient intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his willingneſs to be concealed; all pointing at him, by Letters, or Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, and all enquiries, where he was born, or bred, or how he has acquired the great knowledge he pretends to, and all unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming or oblique deſcriptions, ſhall be induſtriouſly avoided, and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:34354:94"/>that he has not been ſparing in his cenſures of <hi>narrow thoughts, and limited un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> &amp;c. it ſhall not be doubted but on the contrary he is a perſon, of a greater reach, and larger compaſs of thought, and that his underſtanding is not confined, in any part of uſeful know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but only in this of <hi>Trade,</hi> in which the intereſt of the Community is ſo far concerned, that it is hoped the Author will agree, it ought not to be given up in a Complement; but that it is juſt, that what the Author himſelf, ſays, <hi>page</hi> 433, ſhould be obſerved by others. <hi>In a general ſearch after Truth, Errors (whatſoever the perſon be, who commits them) muſt be detected,</hi> which as it was chiefly deſigned, ſo it has been endeavoured and purſued thro' out this whole diſcourſe, with decency and moderation, in which if the writer of this have prevailed, he is well content to be out done in the matter of Reflections, and ill Language.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:34354:94"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
